Tanya Cushman Reviewer:" Peter van de Ven
Thank you very much.
Did you hear what the cow said
to the farmer on a cold winter morning?
Thanks for the warm hand.
Anyway, it's going to get
better, so don't panic on me.
I start small.
Nice to see all of you. How
many of you have never seen me before?
This is your first time.
Oh, wow. Most of you, okay.
I keep thinking for sure I'm more famous
than that, but, you know, that is the truth.
I'm delighted to be here.
Been looking forward to it for a long time.
And it's nice to be back.
You know, I was here not too long ago.
It's nice to be invited back.
It says something.
Maybe it says, let's give him one more chance, right?
See if he can get it right this time.
But I'm delighted to have all of you here.
We're going to spend the day together.
I feel two major responsibilities, and I'm
sure you can guess what those are.
Number one is to make sure
you get your money's worth, right?
When you shell out your cash, especially these days, you want
to make sure you get full value for the money you spent.
And I know the tab for
the seminar will be in the description.
There was not that much.
Pretty modest fee to get in.
Most of you, your tips for the week, right?
So it wasn't that much.
But I want you to be able to say when
you walk out of here today, it was worth my money.
But my biggest responsibility is to
make sure you get your time's worth.
And the reason I say that is
because time is more valuable than money.
In fact, you might start your notes with that.
Time is more valuable than money.
You can get more money.
But unfortunately, you can't.
You can't get more time.
If somebody asks you to spend
your money, that's pretty easy, right?
We live in America.
We're wealthy.
So the money's not the problem.
But what if somebody asks you to spend a day?
Right?
You got to think that over carefully.
And I know you did.
I wouldn't waste one of my days.
Not for anybody.
Not for anything.
Once I understood how valuable
they were, I don't waste any.
But to make an investment like today of
your money and your time, I appreciate that.
Today is going to be costly for me.
It's going to cost me one
of my days to be here.
Right?
And some money of course.
But you know, I don't need the money.
I don't need the money.
And so I'm here not to just joke with
you, I'm here not to just tell some funny stories
and give a performance and walk away.
I'm here to give you some value.
And I want to make it worth your time.
I'm going to invest a little bit of time.
But I'm here to give you some value.
Here's why.
Before we go on, I'll start
off by telling you some funny stories.
I want you to know that when we went up
to the top of the mountain and we ran the
mountain, there were a bunch of mountains there.
So I'm here not to just joke with you. I'm here not
to just tell some funny stories and give a performance and walk away
I'm here to give you some value and
I want to make it worth your time
I'm going to invest a day. You're going to invest a day. Let's
get the most out of it and see what we can walk away
with today
anyway
For you that have not seen me before just very briefly.
Let me just tell you my story. I grew up in Idaho
farm country southwest corner of Idaho
In fact, my father still lives on
the old homestead where I grew up
He'll be 89 his next birthday still hasn't retired
I'm proud of my dad. He's never been ill. He's really
something I'm trying to get him to retire this year 88
I'm telling my father what a good
year to retire when you're 88 and
He says hey talk to me in
10 years, right? I might be ready
But anyway, I went to high school
I graduated
I went to college one year halfway through my second year
of college. I decided I was smart enough so I quit
One of my major mistakes
I should have stayed in school
But I thought yeah, you know, I'm smart enough to get
a job. That's what life's all about right get a job
Pay your bills work hard stay out of trouble
Keep your fingers crossed hope for the best and I figured I
was at least prepared to do that. So I quit college and
went to work and
A little while later got married got my little family going and
I'm out there doing what I thought was the best I could
But about age 25, I'm starting to struggle. I've purchased a
little more than I can conveniently pay for on time and
The creditors are starting to call saying hey you told
us the check was in the mail. What's the deal?
And I'm getting embarrassed by that
I'm also embarrassed big-mouth me with all
the fancy promises I made to get married
I'm way behind on those promises
And I'm getting discouraged wondering what to do and I
thought well, maybe I should go back to school, right?
One year of college pretty short on an application
But you know tough to go back to school, right? Especially when
you got your family going time to stay is when you're there
So I discounted that I thought well if I you know
had my own business that would be the way to go
But you know, I'm short on money too much month
at the end of the money if you've ever been there
That's where I was age 25
So I had to discount that and I'm discouraged wondering where do
I go from here and then the miracle happened for me good fortune
came my way and who can
Explain good fortune. I don't know
Remarkable things that happen to you at
a particular time. Sometimes it's just unexplainable
How those things happen? One of my friends
says well, hey things don't just happen things happen
happen just. Another good note for your
notes. Things don't just happen. Things happen just.
And maybe that's it. I don't know. I'm an
amateur on life, I guess, like most of us are,
trying to figure it out, how to make it valuable.
But I was ready. And my good fortune was at age
25, I met a very wealthy man. His name was
Mr. Shoff, Mr. Earl Shoff. A friend of mine had gone
to work for him. And he started telling me about
this man. He said, you got to meet this man I've
gone to work for. He's wealthy, but he's easy to
talk to. And he's got a unique philosophy of life.
And the more he kept talking about this man,
I thought, well, I've got to meet this man.
So sure enough, shortly after that, I had
a chance to meet this remarkable wealthy man.
And I was impressed. He was wealthy.
Sure enough, he was easy to talk to.
I was so intrigued. Within a few minutes, I
said to myself, if I could be like him,
boy from Idaho, if I could be like him, I'd
give anything. And then I thought, if I could just get
around somebody like him, and if he would teach
me what to do, I would be willing to learn.
I'm coachable. And that was my good fortune. A
few months later, this wealthy man that I met,
Mr. Shoff, took a liking to me, hired me,
gave me a job. I went to work for him.
And I spent the next five years
in his employ. And then unfortunately, he died.
At the end of that period, at age 49. His last
five years, but the first five years of my new life,
I got to spend with this remarkable man. And
my dream came true. He coached me. He taught me.
He taught me the books to read. He taught me
the disciplines. He taught me the changes to make in
my language and personality. And the things he
shared with me during that five years literally
changed my life, turned my life around, changed
my income, changed my bank account, changed my future,
changed everything.
I've never been the same since that unique experience.
And I wish he was still alive today,
Mr. Shoff. I'm sure if he was alive today,
especially after this seminar, Idaho Farm
Boy makes it to Dallas-Fort Worth,
full house, standing room only. Pretty
awesome. I'm sure if he was alive,
I'd be calling him today saying,
you won't believe what's happening to me.
I've had a chance now to share
with other people what you shared with me.
But anyway, how I got here, I don't know. I
don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know.
I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I
30 plus years ago, I was living in Beverly
Hills, California. And one day, a friend of mine,
businessman friend, said, Jim, would you, I'd like to
have you come and share your story with my
service club that I belong to, the Rotary Club.
He said, I know your story. Idaho Farm Boy makes
it to Beverly Hills. But he said, I think my
club members would love to hear your story. He said,
if I arranged one of our breakfast meetings, would
you come tell your story? Just share a few
thoughts. I said, okay.
So I agreed to go give this breakfast talk.
And guess what? They liked it. And my telephone rang.
I got another call, got another call saying,
we heard you've given your story and shared some
ideas. Would you come talk to our club? Talk
to our club. First thing I know, I'm starting to
devote a piece of my business time to giving
these talks. And then one day, a businessman who'd heard
my talk, I think two or three times, approached
me and said, would you come and share that story
and some thoughts with me? And I said, yeah, I'd
love to. And he said, yeah, I'd love to. And I
said, yeah, I'd love to. And he said, yeah, I'd
love to. And I said, yeah, I'd love to. And I
management and salespeople said, I got this little
company going. And he said, if you'd come,
tell your story to my organization, he said, I'd
be happy to pay you. And I thought, wow,
wouldn't that be something? So I agreed to go
do it. And I got paid. Little did I know,
another fortune was waiting for me to translate
my ideas into talks and speeches and seminars.
Now I've written some books. It's on cassette
tape. Now I get to travel around the world.
Last year, I was in Japan
and Israel, Spain, Mexico, Australia, New Zealand,
France, Germany, Canada, and now Dallas forward.
Idaho farm boy gets to travel around the world
and share his story. And here I am today. Anyway,
it's almost too much for me to
comprehend. From where I started, raised in obscurity
in a little small farm community.
And now to be here today is pretty awesome for
me. So anyway, that's just a little bit about my
story. My story is probably more intriguing for me than
it is for you, but I wanted to hear it
again. So I thought I would just bore you with
it. Anyway, I don't ask you to be impressed today.
I'm the one that's impressed from where I came
from to have a chance, but that's the American
dream, right? Come true chance to start
from scratch, start from obscurity, start with pennies,
start with nothing and have a chance
to transform your life, change your life,
set your goals, and then you can start to live your
life. And I think that's a great way to do it.
You can set your goals and see what you
can accomplish. So anyway, that's how I got here.
And I'm just delighted that this day has arrived
and I truly want to make it valuable for you.
Let's go to work. Here's what I hope you'll
find out of this seminar today for your notes.
Here's what I hope you'll find. Number one,
sincerity. Above all else today, I hope you'll
find me sincere.
Best place for people to start to communicate
is sincerity on both sides. I'm sure you're
sincere or you wouldn't be here today, right? To
spend this kind of money, to spend this kind
of time, roll up your sleeves today, go to work
like I am and get this message. You've got to
be sincere. So I assume you're sincere. Now I want
you to see me sincere, but I've got a good
note for you to make. Sincerity is not a test
of truth. Important note to make. Sincerity is not a
test of truth.
Sincerity is not a test of truth. Important note
to make. Sincerity is not a test of truth.
We must not make the mistake of
saying he must be right. He's so sincere
That would be a mistake
And here's why it's possible to be sincerely wrong
So we don't mistake
Sincerity for truth right sincerity is only a test
of sincerity truth has to yet be tested by truth
Okay, but hopefully you will find me sincere and truthful
Next a combination of things. I hope
you'll find here today ideas plus inspiration
Ideas plus inspiration
Ideas business ideas and social ideas
and personal ideas. We all need ideas
Right how to have a good day ideas how to have a good
year ideas how to have your best year ever ideas good health ideas
Personal relationship ideas how to
deal with your family ideas salesman
management ideas
Financial freedom for the future ideas. We all need good
ideas. So today I hope you gather up by notes and
By what you can remember a lot of ideas
I want to share as many with you as
I possibly can and the time constraints we have
Today is going to go very rapidly. I used to
think a day like this was a long day found out
It's pretty short day, but I'm gonna go as fast as I can
share with you as many ideas as I possibly can and here's why
Ideas can be life-changing
Ideas can be life-changing and sometimes all you need
is just one more in a series of good ideas
It's like dialing the
numbers into the lock
Right, you got five or six numbers dialed
into the lock the lock still won't come open
But you don't need five or six more numbers
Maybe you just need one more and maybe a seminar
like this could do it a sermon could do it
The lyrics from a song could do it
the dialogue from a movie could do it
Conversation with a friend might do it that one
last piece you need number dial it into the lock
That's it. The lock comes open
There's the door for you to walk through and maybe
this seminar today could furnish that for you one more idea
I know you've come with a lot already
Sometimes we get the impression I used to have that but I
only had this much going for me and I needed this much
Usually not true, and I'm sure not true of this audience
where I find you today as well dressed as you look today
You know as fine as you are sitting here today
It isn't that you know, you've got this
much going for you and you need this much
I would assume you've got this much going for you and
maybe all you need is just a few more thoughts ideas
To furnish you some ways and means to turn
your life into the dream you want it to be
So ideas the seminars gonna be loaded with
ideas. I want you to take good notes
but here's what else I hope you'll
find here today and that is inspiration and
Who knows the mystery of inspiration why
some people are inspired and some are not
You were inspired to get here some were not
who knows the mystery of that. I don't know
How come you made it?
The rest of them didn't make it.
We don't know what that mystery is
Some people turned it down some people said cost too
much some people said it's gonna take too much time
Some people are too busy
Right a lot of different excuses why some are inspired to
take advantage of something that comes to town others pass it
Up we don't know the mystery to that
Here's what I call it mysteries of the mind
and I just leave it at that some things
I don't try to figure out
I take the simple approach now
right
Some people do and some people don't I
mean that's about as profound as my philosophy is
some by and
I'm don't buy some go for it and
some don't some change and
Some don't and if you've been around for a while, you
can usually work out the numbers right out of 10, you know
Three do, seven don't.
Whatever business you're involved in, pretty
soon you got this ratio going.
The ones that do, the ones that don't.
You say, well, why don't the ones that don't?
How come they don't?
We don't know.
I just leave it as a mystery.
I used to try to understand all that.
I just take the simple approach now.
The guy says, this happens to me, this
happens to me, this goes wrong for me,
and all this stuff goes wrong for me.
How come all this stuff happens to me?
I say, I don't know, beats me.
The best I've been able to figure out is
those kind of things always happen to people like you.
I mean, right?
That's the best I got.
I don't know.
I'm an amateur on this stuff.
What do I know?
So just take the simple approach, right?
That's how it is.
Who knows?
Interesting story says, the day
the Christian church was started.
Now, I'm an amateur on the
Bible, but best account I can remember,
the day the Christian church was started,
a man named David, who was
a pastor in the United States,
a magnificent sermon was preached.
Great presentation.
And if you're a student at all of good communication,
it was one of the classic presentations of all times.
The sermon, the first day the Christian church was started.
And it said, this sermon, this
presentation was given to a multitude,
meaning a lot of people.
But it was interesting, as
the account gives us the record,
it says, when the sermon was finished,
there was a variety of reaction to the same sermon.
Isn't that interesting?
Isn't that fascinating?
I find it fascinating.
It said, some that heard this presentation were perplexed.
And I read the presentation,
sounded pretty straightforward to me,
said, why would somebody be perplexed
with a good, sincere, straightforward presentation?
Best answer I've got, they are the perplexed.
I mean, you know, what other explanation is there?
It doesn't matter who's preaching.
It said, some that heard
this presentation mocked and laughed,
made fun of the presentation.
I thought, hey, this looks pretty sincere to me.
If you give a sincere, honest
presentation, why would somebody mock and laugh?
Easy explanation.
They are the mockers and the laughers.
What else would you expect them to do?
Right.
I used to try to straighten all that out.
Say, well, they shouldn't do that.
I don't do that anymore.
I've got peace of mind now.
I sleep like a baby.
Not try to straighten all this stuff out.
I used to be so naive.
I used to say, well, liar shouldn't lie.
See, how naive can you be?
Of course.
They're supposed to lie.
That's why we call them liars.
They lie.
So I don't straighten this stuff out anymore.
Anyway, it said, some that heard this
magnificent presentation didn't know what was going on.
And they're usually easy to spot.
They're usually saying, what's going on?
Right.
I mean, they don't know what's going on.
But interesting, right?
A variety of reaction to
the same sincere, honest presentation.
Now, it also says in
wrapping it up, some that heard.
The presentation believed.
And I think that's who the speaker was looking for.
The believers.
Interesting.
Now, it said the number of believers was about 3000.
So pretty good first day.
I've had some first days.
I never had 3000.
But anyway, 3000 were believers.
And that's the speaker was looking
for the believers out of this multitude.
And that's about as close as
we can come to understanding the mystery.
Some believe and some mock and
some laugh and some are perplexed.
And some are not.
Some don't know what's going on.
And you just have to leave it that way.
Why?
Because that's the way it's going to be.
The way to be brilliant is to find out how it's
going to be and then say, here's how it should be.
I mean, that's how you become brilliant.
So anyway, who knows the mystery?
I call it mysteries of the mind.
We don't understand.
But I don't try to change it anymore.
On this particular story, as far as we know, they didn't
have classes after the presentation to try to de-perplex the perplexed.
I mean, as far as
we know, they left them perplexed.
They left the mockers mocking.
They let the laughers laugh.
I mean, they didn't come back
and try to straighten all this out.
You say, well, how can you build a church?
Well, make another presentation.
You'll get some believers and some mockers and some
laughers and some who don't know what's going on.
So that's about the best we can do.
So but I'm glad I've got the believers here today.
You believed enough to shell out your cash and part
with your time and some of your effort and energy.
And I appreciate that.
So hopefully you'll find some inspiration here today.
All right.
To get the most out of today.
A couple more notes.
Number one, be thankful.
That's a good way to capture
the most of a day like this.
Be thankful for what you already have.
That shouldn't be any problem in America.
Being thankful.
Everything we need is available in America.
Everybody wants to come here.
Right.
The last time I was
here, that little presentation I gave.
Everybody wants to come here.
America.
People haven't plotted and schemed the last 40 years.
Say.
And if I don't have a
plan, I'm going to come here.
If I could just get
to Poland, everything would be OK.
No, everybody wants to come to America.
Why?
Everything's available here.
All the books you need.
All the sermons you need.
All the churches you need.
All the schools you need.
All the instruction you need.
All the inspiration you need.
All the capital you need.
All the markets you need.
All the challenge you need.
All the information you need.
All the seminars you need.
Everything's available here.
This is America.
So number one, let's be
thankful for what we already have.
Thanksgiving does this.
Opens up the doors.
Opens up the windows.
Opens up the channels.
Thanksgiving for what you already have.
I did a seminar one weekend up
at the ranch up at Clear Lake.
Got a lodge up there.
Nice setting.
High Valley.
High Serenity Ranch.
For the weekend, Friday evening, Saturday, Sunday.
People drove in from around California.
I got there late Friday afternoon.
Everybody had pretty well already gotten there.
I couldn't believe the parking lot.
Continental's and Eldorado's and Mercedes and Cadillacs.
Unbelievable.
Ferrari.
One Rolls Royce.
Unbelievable.
I walked in.
Good looking crowd like this, sitting
there ready for the weekend seminar.
My opening remarks were, ladies and gentlemen, I think
the rest of the world would find it strange
that we have all come here this weekend
to try to figure out how to do better.
I think the rest of the
world would say, I don't understand.
Guy and his Rolls Royce.
I got to get to the seminar.
I've found it pretty complicated.
out how to get another one of these
Rolls Royces. Unbelievable. Anyway, let's be thankful. Here's
what locks up the doors and the channels
to receive more cynicism. That locks you away.
That prevents you from learning more. Being
a cynic about the past and the future,
a cynic about the marketplace, cynical
about the people, cynical about the institutions,
cynical about the setup, cynical about yourself,
cynical about your chances. See, that locks away
all the chance for stuff to flow your way.
So good advice, I think, today. Start off, be thankful.
Here's number two, listen well. That's going
to be a challenge today. I understand that.
Seems like most of our life is
still going on outside these four walls, right?
Most of our life is still
going on outside these four walls.
going on outside these four walls, right?
Most of our life seems like it's
all continuing out there. Family and business and
associates and market and economy and whatever else
is happening in the midst of your life.
And to sort of pull your attention from what's going
on out there and put it in here for just
a few hours, I know is a challenge.
But do the best you can, listen well.
And here's the last one, take
good notes. Be a good student today.
Take some good notes. I've not come to
entertain you. As you can tell by my
opening joke, right? I would
not make it in Las Vegas.
So we don't have a dog
and pony show today, no entertainment.
But I do have some ideas. Take some good
notes. Somebody showed me the other day notes that they
took about 21 years ago, attending one
of my seminars out in Los Angeles.
He said, I still use these notes I took
21 years ago to help me in my business,
relationship with my family. So I'd like to have
these notes that you take today become that value.
I'd like to have them be valuable for you.
Then it would be worth me making the investment
to come and spend a portion of
my life, my time, my energy here.
And I want this investment I'm making here today to pay
off. And one of the ways it can pay off for
me is for you to take good notes
and then go away and use whatever makes sense.
Because what I feast on coming back around is
the stories out of this audience today, sure enough,
six weeks from now, six months from now, six
years from now, somebody's going to by phone, by letter,
by letter, by email, by phone numbernell, by
the number. I want you all to be all
busy.
In fact, Application rooms have their own is rooms. My daughter says, I
can do them all by myself. It'd be good when you have one!
Don't be a follower, be a student.
You'd be happy to know
today we haven't come seeking disciples.
We've got no movement for you to join.
I'm just here to share some of
my experiences, good ideas, best I can.
But I think that's good advice.
Don't be a follower, be a student, right?
Take advice, but not orders.
Take information, but don't let
somebody, you know, order your life.
Make sure what you do is
the product of your own conclusion.
Excellent note to make.
Make sure what you do is
the product of your own conclusion.
Not to do what someone else says.
Take what someone else says, process
it, think about it, ponder it.
If it makes you wonder, if
it makes you think, then it's valuable.
Then when you go take action, make sure that
the action is not what somebody told you to do.
Make sure the action is
the product of your own conclusion.
If you'll follow just a
little bit of those simple guidelines,
I'm telling you, the learning
process can be speedy, swift, powerful.
Your learning curve can go up and then applying it to
your business, your life, your family, conversations, equities of all kinds.
You'll find some progress like I did that first five years when
I met a teacher willing to share with me, turn my life around.
Progress I couldn't believe happened for me.
Okay.
Let's get started.
I want to review.
I was here last time and
we talked about the five major pieces.
The life puzzle.
And I just want to review those because it lays such a good
foundation for all the rest that I want to share with you today.
We got a lot of subjects to cover.
So we're going to go rather swiftly.
Okay.
Put on your mental track shoes here and run with
me today because I'm going to deal mostly in concepts.
Expect you to fill in a lot of
the details because I got a lot to share.
I want to get through it all.
But let's lay this foundation
again of the five major pieces.
Happens to be the title of my latest book.
But I think it is
so valuable in laying a foundation.
It's some of the things I
learned between ages 25 and 30.
The teacher who taught me taught me so well.
He dealt in these fundamentals.
We call these fundamentals.
We call these basics.
Basics for sports.
Fundamentals for sports.
Fundamentals for your business.
Fundamentals for the way you deal with your family.
A few simple things.
A few basic things that if you practice every
day can make all the difference in the world.
How it works out.
I boiled it down to five
major pieces to the life puzzle.
Let's just review those.
Number one is philosophy.
Philosophy, as I taught the last time I was here, philosophy, in my
personal opinion, is the major determining factor in how your life works out.
Philosophy.
The major determining factor in how your life works out.
To form our philosophy, you've got to think.
You've got to use your mind.
You've got to process ideas.
And this whole process over a lifetime, starting way back here when we were children, schools that we've attended,
our parents, our experiences, all this stuff that we've processed by the thinking process helps to develop our philosophy.
And in my opinion, each person's personal philosophy is
the major factor in how your life works out.
Here's what I called it in
that last presentation when I was here.
It's called the set of the sale.
Each person's personal philosophy is
like the set of the sale.
Now, I used to think it
was circumstances that ordered my life.
If someone would have asked me at age
25, Mr. Rohn, how come you're not doing well?
Pennies in your pocket, creditors calling, nothing in
the bank, behind on your promises to your family.
You live in America, 25 years old.
Got a beautiful family, every reason to do well.
And things are not going that well for you.
What is wrong here?
It would not have occurred
to me to blame my philosophy.
I mean, it would not have occurred to me.
Say, well, I got this lousy philosophy and that's how come
I got pennies in my pocket and nothing in the bank.
Things aren't working well.
That would not have occurred to me.
I found it much easier to blame the government.
Much easier to blame the tax problem.
I used to say taxes are two.
High.
Top tax rate when I first started paying taxes.
Back then when your income reached a
certain level, all your income over that, 91%.
So I used to say that's too high.
Now the tax, top tax rate is about 33%.
But people are still saying what?
Taxes are two.
See, but you can't use that anymore.
If it's gone from 91 to
33, how could it be too high?
Come on.
I threw all that old excuse stuff away.
Some people found it though,
and they're using it these days.
My old list.
I used to blame the traffic, the weather.
I used to blame circumstances.
Right?
People say I'm too tall.
I'm too short.
I'm too old.
I was raised in obscurity, raised on a farm.
Parents of modest means.
All the stuff.
If you were to ask me, how come you find yourself here,
Mr. Rohn, age 25, living in America, land of abundance and opportunity?
Pennies, zero in the bank,
not doing well, creditors calling.
It would not have occurred
to me to blame my philosophy.
I found it easier to blame the company, company policy.
I used to say, if this is all they
pay, how do they expect you to do well?
So I figured that, you know, my future was going to be
tied to what everybody else was arranging, the economy and right interest rates.
I used to say things cost too much.
That was my whole explanation, not my philosophy.
Until my teacher taught me better
that this is where the problem was.
My own personal philosophy.
Here's what's exciting about
each person's personal philosophy.
That's what makes us different than dogs and
animals and birds and cats and spiders and alligators.
That's what makes us different
than all of the life forms.
The ability to think, the ability to use your mind,
the ability to process ideas and not just operate by instinct.
In the winter, I'm telling you,
the goose can only fly south.
What if south doesn't look too good?
Tough luck.
It can only fly south.
But see, human beings are not
like a goose, can only fly south.
I mean, you can turn around, go north, you can go east, you
can go west, you can order the entire process of your own life.
And we do that by the way we think.
We do that by exercising our minds.
We do that by processing ideas and come up
with a better philosophy, a better strategy for our life.
Goals for the future.
Okay.
Plans to achieve those goals.
All this comes from developing our philosophy.
Philosophy helps us to process what's available.
Well, when we get here, we got seed and we got
soil and we got some rain and we've got some what?
Sunshine and we've got some seasons and what?
The miracle of life.
Now the key is what do
you do with all this stuff?
How do you turn all this stuff that's available here
into equity and promise and lifestyle and dreams and future possibilities?
All of this that's possible now with human beings.
How do you take all this stuff
and turn it into this equities and values?
Well, it starts with philosophy.
What is the seed?
What is the soil?
What is the sunshine?
What is the rain?
Is it possible to take some of each of all the stuff that's available
and turn it into food and turn it into value and turn it into nourishment?
Turn it into something spectacular and unique
that no other life form can do?
And the answer is yes.
But you cannot deal with all this stuff and what
to do with it unless you start refining your philosophy.
Think.
Use your mind.
Come up with ideas and strengthen your philosophy.
So the seed and the soil and the rain and the sunshine, this is called, you know, the economy and the banks and the
money and the schools and everything that's available out there, processing information, what to do with all that and turn it into equity and value.
That is the major challenge of life.
My personal opinion.
So each person's personal philosophy now is going to determine what
you're going to do with seed and soil and sunshine and rain.
The change of seasons.
That's it.
My personal opinion.
Each person's personal philosophy is
like the set of the sale.
That's what this seminar is for today.
Help you to trim a better sale.
You don't need a better economy.
You don't need better seed and soil.
In fact, when it comes to seed and soil and rain and
sunshine and seasons and the miracle of life, that's all you got.
Now, what if you blame this stuff?
Then you're blaming all you got.
You can't blame this stuff.
You can't blame the people but you
can't blame all the people in your life.
You have to blame everything.
And you have to blame anything, and what happens?
It's because you're blaming this.
You're blaming the enemy.
You're blaming the world.
In fact when it comes to seed and soil and
rain and sunshine and seasons and the miracle of life
That's all you got now. What if you
blame this stuff then you're blaming all you got
If you blame the economy and you blame the schools and you
blame the teachers and you blame the sermons and the preachers and
And you blame, you know the marketplace and you
blame the company and company policy. What else is there?
When some people get through with
their blame list, there is nothing else
That's all there is and if you blame
The only thing you've got to work
with I'm telling you it's called mistake colossal
in not understanding
That that's all you've got to work with and if this is
all you've got to work with then you don't change the seed and
You don't change the soil and you don't change
the rain and you don't change the Sun sign
You don't change the seasons, right
guys says I'll take three springs
four summers
nine falls
No winters and no
You can't fool with this stuff. You
got to take it like it comes then
What do you change to make your life
work? Well, you got to start with your philosophy
Guess what I had to do at age 25 in order
to change my own future. I had to change my mind
I had to change my thinking
I had to change my philosophy
I was messed up on what was causing my problem and once I
got that straightened out that all the stuff I blamed the government and
taxes and
The marketplace and the economy and things
cost too much negative relatives cynical neighbors
Once I got rid of that and started going
for where the real problem was, which was me
I'm telling you my life exploded into change
My bank account changed
immediately my income changed immediately
My whole life took on a whole new look and color
immediately and the early results I got from making these philosophical changes
Tasted so good. I've never stopped the process from that
day until this and I'm telling you with a little
consideration of the refinement of your sale
By setting a better sale refining your philosophy your whole life can
start to change from today on you don't have to wait till tomorrow
You don't have to wait till next month. You don't
have to wait till spring. Don't have to wait till 93
You can start this whole process
Immediately I recommend it
Now some people do so little thinking
they don't even have their sale up
I mean you can imagine where they're gonna wind up at the
end of this week at the end of this month at the end
of this year
Now's the chance to change process all this information
So number one is philosophy
Okay, and we dealt with all that where we
get ideas from personal experience from other people's experiences
I don't want to get into all those details
because we covered that the last time I was here
But philosophy that's number one my personal opinion
Each person's personal philosophy. Here's the definition of success
and failure. Just make this note. Here's failure a
few
Errors and mistakes
in judgment, repeated every day.
Now you can automatically assume Mr. Rohn,
I say, I can understand that.
A few errors in judgment
repeated every day for six years.
I'm with my father, I think I told this story
the last time I was here.
My father, 88 years old, he's never been ill,
still hasn't retired.
Not long ago, midnight, we're
getting ready to go to bed.
We've drilled a new well, got some extra water,
got some more acres going, he's all excited.
At midnight, we're getting ready to go to bed.
My father's eating what he calls his midnight snack,
a little bite to eat before you go to bed.
Don't have to go to bed hungry.
And I'm watching him eat this midnight snack.
Guess what he had?
An apple, few graham crackers,
and a glass of grapefruit juice.
I said, no wonder my father's so healthy.
My mom taught us all those good health practices.
Taught me when I'm growing up, right?
I'm an only child, I've never been ill.
Passed a big 5-0 some time ago.
My two daughters, 32, 33, never been ill.
My grandkids, never been ill.
Telling you, the legacy lingers on.
As I watched my father have this midnight snack,
suddenly it occurred to me.
I know that's part of it.
An apple, what?
A day, that's gotten to Dallas-Fort Worth, right?
An apple.
A day.
Keeps the doctor away.
Good question for this intelligent audience.
What if that's true?
You say, well, Mr. Rohn, if that's true,
that would be easy to do.
Then what's the problem?
It's easy not to do.
It's easy not to adopt
it as your own personal philosophy.
Or the guy messed up to say.
Guy says a Hershey bar a day, say no.
No.
You've been watching too much television.
It is not Hershey bar.
You gotta be smarter in philosophy
than to fall for the Hershey bar a day
when it's an apple a day.
You gotta be smarter than that.
And if you make that
kind of an error in judgment
every day for six years,
I'm telling you, it'll accumulate into disaster.
Sometimes the first year you say, well, you know,
I'm so healthy now, what difference is it gonna make?
You gotta be smarter than that.
Just because disaster doesn't fall on us
at the end of the first day,
doesn't mean disaster isn't coming.
You gotta be so smart that
you look down the road and say,
will the errors in my present judgment of philosophy,
what's that gonna cost me in one year,
six years, one month, six months?
I'm telling you the money cost and the health cost
and the success cost is too gigantic.
If you'll look down the road a little ways.
And say, are there errors in my current judgment
like an apple versus a Hershey bar?
Is that just a good illustration
of some of the rest of my errors in judgment?
If it is, that's where
I found myself at age 25.
I started working when I was 19.
I met my teacher who helped turn my life around
when I was 25, that's six years.
At the end of the first
six years of my economic life,
I've got pennies in my pocket.
I've got nothing in the bank.
The creditors are calling saying,
hey, you told us the check was in the mail.
I'm embarrassed.
I'm behind on my promises.
I live in America.
I'm 25 year old American male.
I got a nice family, every reason to do well.
And I'm messed up.
Now what's messed up?
I used to think it was
the community that was messed up
and the country was messed up
and the government was messed up.
If those Democrats ever get in the White House,
that'll really mess things up.
If the Republicans stay in power,
The economy was messed up.
Interest rates are messed up.
I thought all this stuff was messed up.
Then I found out that's not what was messed up.
I was criticizing the only
thing I had to work with.
What was really messed up was my own personal philosophy.
My own errors in judgment,
in my own personal philosophy,
brought me in six years to pennies in my pocket,
nothing in the bank,
and trying to explain why I wasn't doing well,
living in America,
25 year old American male,
got a family, every reason to do well.
Now, once I understood this,
here's the formula for failure,
errors in judgment,
being lax about developing your own personal philosophy,
I'm telling you, it's called accumulated disaster.
It doesn't matter whether it's your health
or your bank account.
Guy's got an empty bank account,
probably has high cholesterol.
Why?
Over the last six years,
he never paid attention to either one.
And it doesn't matter whether it's a dollar
or whether it's your money
or whether it's your cholesterol count.
All you got to do is commit the errors.
And just because disaster doesn't fall on you
at the end of the first
day that you don't eat an apple,
you say, well, I didn't eat an apple today
and tonight I'm not ill.
Well, you gotta be brighter than that.
Someday you gotta leave first grade.
The reason we make those first grade desks so small
so they won't fit at age 25,
I mean, right?
You don't belong here anymore.
Come on.
Now, let me give you the second part.
I'm gonna give you the second part.
The secret to success.
The formula for failure,
a few errors in judgment
repeated every day for one month
starts the weakness, starts the disaster process.
You can imagine what happens in six years.
Now here's the formula for success.
A few simple disciplines practiced every day.
And you've started a whole new process
called a whole new life.
A few simple disciplines practiced
every day.
And if you decide today to go for the apple
instead of the Hershey bar,
I'm telling you, you have begun the process
of turning your life around.
And if you keep up that process,
not only with your health habits,
but with your money habits
and with your communication habits,
with your sales habits and management habits
and every other habit that you've got,
if you'll start that process,
eliminate the errors and replace it
with disciplines practiced,
I'm telling you, you can start this process
of life change immediately.
After today, you don't need to do anything.
After today, you don't ever
have to be the same again.
Only by choice.
You don't have to walk out of here
the same as you walked in today.
Only by choice.
You can start a whole new process.
And you say, well, Mr. Rohn, is it that simple?
Yes, it's that simple.
Where else would you start?
But with an apple.
You don't have to start with something staggering.
What if you should be walking around the block
for your good health and you don't?
What'll that do in six years?
I'm telling you, the word is disaster.
You could and you should and you don't.
Here's an even stronger word.
You won't.
I mean, don't might mean you're careless.
Won't probably means you're stubborn.
And either one's called disaster.
Could, should, don't.
I'm telling you, that's why
at the end of five years,
six years, I found myself with pennies in my pocket,
I found myself with pennies in my pocket,
nothing in the bank, creditors calling.
Could, should, won't.
Could, should, don't is called disaster.
Now, how do you change all that?
The next six years, I got rich.
The next six years, I became a millionaire.
By the time I'm 31, I'm a millionaire.
How about that?
You say, well, Mr. Rohn, what happened?
Well, strangely enough, during that second six years
of my economic life, the government was about the same.
I'm telling you, taxes were about?
The same.
My negative relatives were?
I'm telling you, the economy was about?
The same, and prices were about the same,
and everything else was about the same.
Circumstances were about the same.
Then how come I got rich?
How come I totally changed my life?
I was not the same.
Somebody says, well, what did you go to work on
to do all that?
I started with my philosophy.
I started amending my errors by doing some better thinking,
changing my mind, coming up with ideas,
ideas that I didn't have before I met my teacher.
And once that whole process started for me,
I'm telling you, I changed my whole life.
Within a six year period, I was never the same.
And I've kept up that process all these years.
One of the reasons why I'm
here is to continue my craft.
I don't want the day to come someday somebody says,
you should have heard Jim Rohn 10 years ago
when he was really terrific.
Guess what I want people to say?
I heard him 10 years ago,
but you should hear him now.
I'm telling you, the man works on his craft.
I'm telling you, the man's done some extra reading.
I'm telling you, the man doesn't miss a trick.
I'm telling you, he's worked hard on himself.
That's why he's able to deliver like he does.
The same thing can happen for you as a teenager.
It can happen to you
as a mother, as a father,
as a business person, as
a sales person, running a business.
Doesn't matter, management, wherever you find yourself.
This is the process called personal change.
And what I say to start with is,
start with your own philosophy.
Your philosophy is gonna determine
whether or not you go for the disciplines
or continue the errors that's called potential disaster.
And everybody has it within their power.
What was so happy for me
to find out at age 25,
Mr. Shove said, Mr. Rohn,
you don't have to change countries,
but you do have to change philosophy.
And if you'll change philosophy, not country,
you can turn around your income,
you can turn around your bank account,
you can turn around your skills,
you can become capable, powerful, sophisticated, healthy,
influential,
all the other equities that you could possibly want
out of your life using the only stuff there is
and not trying to change any of this stuff.
Appreciate all of this stuff with
all of its ups and downs,
with all of its mystery of why it works
and sometimes it doesn't work.
Don't challenge this.
You don't have to ask for another planet.
You don't have to ask for another country.
Just ask for another book.
Ask for another seminar.
Ask for another idea.
And you can start this
whole process of personal life change.
Now I could spend the whole day on philosophy
because that's where it is.
If I could get you intrigued
with that enough to study it,
enough to ponder it to
where you'd pick up the commitment
like I did and say, hey,
as simple as an apple a day,
as simple as a walk around the block,
why not start right there?
If you don't start there, where
else are you going to start?
Might as well start where it's easy
and then go to the more complicated disciplines.
Because if you can't handle the complicated,
the simple disciplines,
how can you handle the complicated ones?
Okay.
Key.
Philosophy.
Here's number two.
I got to give these now very quickly
because I got too much to
cover here to linger too long.
Number one, we're affected by philosophy.
First major of the five major pieces.
Number two is attitude.
We're affected by how we feel.
First, we're affected by what we know
and the decisions we make.
Second, we're affected by attitude.
How we feel.
And I gave that quick list.
Let me give it to you.
It's how you feel about the past.
You got to have a good attitude about the past.
Use it as a school, not a club.
Don't beat yourself to death with your past.
Faults, failures, losses.
Let the past be a school.
Harsh school, maybe.
What else is new?
Let the past be a school master to teach you.
Not to threaten you, but to teach you.
Okay.
Number three,
we're affected by our own behavior.
We're affected by our own behavior.
Next, it's how you feel about the future.
Set your goals.
We'll talk a little bit about that
before we finish today.
Goal setting.
The promise of the future is an awesome force
to affect your life every day.
Without a future well designed,
we take hesitant steps.
And all you have to have is hesitant steps.
For six years, you'll be timid, driven into a corner,
not boldly willing to go and take your portion,
take your share.
Okay.
Next, it's how you feel about everybody else.
Gotta have a good attitude about everybody else
because it takes everybody else to make a market.
One person doesn't make a family.
One person doesn't make a business.
One person doesn't make a corporation.
One person doesn't make a community.
One person doesn't make a nation.
It takes all of us to make a dynamic economy,
a nation second to none.
It takes all of us to make the churches
and make the economy run.
Takes all of us to make the possibilities.
All the gifts that have flowed in here
the last 200 years,
unprecedented in six and a half thousand years
of recorded history.
There's been nothing like it.
The ethnic streams that have flowed in here
brought their gifts, brought their talent,
brought their skills, brought their inventions,
brought their work ethic.
All of it mixed together is called America.
Been nothing like it in
six and a half thousand years.
And to miss the value
of it by some, you know,
warped attitude about it,
I'm telling you, you've missed it all.
And if you have an appreciation for it all,
you'll draw from it.
And if you draw from all the gifts
that have been blended together here, from the people,
blended together here for 200 years now
for your value and benefit,
think of what you can do for your days,
for your business, for your conversation,
for your equities.
You can transform it to an incredible degree.
And here's the last one.
It's how you feel about yourself.
Understanding self-worth is the beginning of progress.
Self-worth should be easy.
If one of us can do
it, all of us can do it.
If anybody can think it, we all can think it.
I can read.
I can understand.
You can understand.
From where I came from,
the few simple things I did and tried
revolutionized my life in five years.
There isn't anybody here that can't do it.
Change from pennies to fortune.
Change from nothing to something.
Change from broke to rich.
Anybody in this room can do it.
If any of us can do
it, we all can do it.
That's the kind of value you should place on yourself.
If Jim Rohn can understand it, I can understand it.
If he can read, I can read.
If he can find it, I can find it.
If he can change, I can change.
If he can get it
done, I can get it done.
That's the attitude.
It's about yourself.
So valuable.
Now, in transforming our lives,
we don't start with attitude.
We don't start with the inspiration here.
We start with education.
Somebody says, well, I expected you
to just come get motivated today.
Well, that probably won't do it.
Somebody says, by now, we
should be standing on the chairs,
waving a flag, singing the old gray mare.
Get going here.
No, that's not where you start.
Life change does not start with inspiration.
Life change starts
with education.
You've got to be educated to the
point of where you might have messed up.
My teacher put it in blunt, simple language.
He only went to the ninth grade in
school, so he put it in simple language.
I could understand.
He said, Mr. Rohn, after six years
living in America, healthy American male, 25 years
old, been working six years, one year of
college, pennies in your pocket, nothing in the bank,
behind on your promises.
Shove said, I just got one simple explanation for that.
You've messed up.
Now I could understand that kind of language.
Substitute a Hershey bar for
an apple means you've messed up.
Should walk around the block.
Could walk around the block.
Won't walk around the block.
You have messed up.
And all you've got to go
is write down through the list.
Don't need some teacher to come by and tell you.
Be your own best teacher saying, hey, let
me make a list of some places I've messed
up.
Because if I let this down, let this down.
That probably affects me.
I'm going to have to go to the rest.
And the answer is that's true.
So we don't start with inspiration.
We start with education.
Somebody says, well, just motivate this guy.
He'll be all right.
Just motivate him.
Get him turned on.
Probably not.
If a guy's an idiot, you motivate him.
Now you've got a motivated idiot.
No, it won't be all right.
So we start with education.
What's the first education?
If it isn't going well and you
live in America, you have messed up.
You don't have a job.
You don't need to change countries.
You say, well, the country's messed up.
That's like cursing the soil and cursing the
seed and the sunshine and the rain, which
is all you got.
Don't curse all you got.
When you get your own planet,
you can rearrange this whole deal.
This one you got to take like it comes.
So number two is attitude.
Here was number three activity.
This is the work part.
The labor part.
Taking action.
The activity is the miracle working piece.
A miracle being something we
don't quite understand how it works.
Doesn't mean it doesn't work.
It means we just don't quite understand how it works.
Miracles work.
God says, I'm an amateur on
God, but here's my best analysis.
God says, if you'll plant
the seed, I'll make the tree.
Now that's a good arrangement.
I'm an amateur on God.
Number one gives God the tough end of the deal.
What if you had to make the tree that
keep you up late night trying to figure out how
do you make a tree?
Say no, I'm telling you the mystery and
the miracle of this stuff has already been set
up.
God says, I got the miracle going.
I got the seasons going.
I got some sunshine and some rain and I'm God.
But the way I've arranged that I just need
somebody to plant the seed, not chant in California.
There.
I'm trying to chant.
Get this stuff done.
Forget this California stuff.
You don't have to rub a
crystal and sleep under a pyramid.
This stuff too easy.
Getting rich is too easy.
Changing your life is too easy.
Forget all that.
Right?
Massive bombard affirmation.
Forget all that.
My opinion, ocean waves and seagulls.
Come on.
This stuff's too simple.
Just simple, easy stuff.
But if you neglect it, that's
how it piles up year after year.
But if you're willing to straighten it out.
And here's one of the keys.
It's called activity.
It's called disciplines.
Turning wisdom from your philosophy and inspiration,
the strengthening of attitude and faith, courage,
commitment and all this stuff that comes from attitude.
If you're willing to take these two
qualities, philosophy and attitude, and invest it into
activity, you can have a miracle.
Anything short of that.
You can have a miracle.
Wisdom doesn't perform a miracle.
Attitude doesn't perform a miracle.
The only thing that performs a miracle of
increase called equity is called putting wisdom and
attitude into discipline, into labor.
And this labor now can perform a miracle.
And here's the two parts to the labor.
One, do what you can.
Number two, do the best you can.
Can't give you better advice than that.
Number one, do what you can.
You just got to go home
and make a list after today.
Okay?
And here's the question to ask
as you make this personal list.
What am I not doing that would be easy
to do that could greatly change my health, my
wealth?
What am I not doing I'm
neglecting that would be easy to do?
Just go home and answer that question personally.
You don't have to put the
answers on a public bulletin board.
This is just all personal stuff.
From the walk around the block to the apple,
to what to do with your money, which we're
going to cover today.
What does a child do with a dollar?
We're going to cover that today.
Errors and judgment, disaster.
A few simple disciplines, wealth beyond imagination.
And if you'll pick up the activity part,
the miracle working part, plant the seed part,
take care of your part.
The soil will take care of its part
and the seed will take care of its part.
The seasons will take care of their part.
The miracle will take care of its part.
If you'll take care of your
part called putting it into activity, action.
Work's miracles.
2000 years ago on April 13th, one of Jesus disciples.
Now again, I'm an amateur on the Bible.
The best as I can remember it.
One of Jesus disciples said to Jesus, it's time
to pay our taxes and we don't have any
money.
That's how come I know it was about April 13th.
Okay.
To this statement by his disciple, Jesus said,
best as I can read the record, Jesus said,
no problem.
Now why could he say no problem?
Well, word has it word has it.
He was a miracle worker.
Word has it.
If you're a good student of history, word has it.
He was a miracle worker.
If you handed a problem to a miracle
worker, what would he be inclined to say?
No problem.
You got to hang out with folks like that. I
Belong to a small group like
that. We do business around the world
You hand these guys a problem. They say no problem.
What how many books would they read to solve it?
Many as it takes how early would they get up?
Early as it takes how much information would they get?
Much as they needed so it's what?
No problem. You got to
hang out with folks like that
You said this will be no problem the tax thing
he said to his disciple it's simple go fishing Wow
Now that was easy for this particular disciple
his name was Peter and Peter was a
fisherman how clever
How clever?
But here's the real problem if you should fish
And you could fish and you
don't fish you got no miracle
You could change you should change
You won't change
That's called accumulated disaster in six
years. You'll be explaining instead of celebrating
Having some ragged list like I had reasons
for not doing well pennies in my pocket
Could should don't
And if you'll just start the process of change could
Should and will you can start this whole process
and if you will then put it into action
The miracle belongs to you
Jesus said to his disciple. It'll be simple go fishing
and the first fish you catch look in his mouth
Peter said okay. He was used
to strange things happening in this relationship
Peter goes fishing catches the first fish looks in
his mouth. Guess what's in the fish's mouth coins
Peter says wow coins
Starts counting the value of these coins and when he
adds it up guess how much it added up to
Exactly enough money to pay his taxes and Jesus taxes
Which gives you Jesus position on taxes
Now we call that what a
miracle
A miracle only because we don't quite understand
how it works. It doesn't mean it doesn't work
It simply means we don't quite understand how it works
But here's how you get
a miracle going for your life
Number one do what you can get a list
of the stuff you could do and you haven't done
Postpone and start cleaning that up. You can't
start at a better place for personal change
That'll affect your bank account affect your future affect
your income affect everything. You can't start a better
life change process than
Cleaning up what you should be doing the
man says well my mother lives down in Florida
Should have written her six months ago. I
just can't seem to get that letter written
I'm asking you to get that letter written clean that up and
don't walk like other people walk don't postpone like other people postpone
You say well, is it as simple as
writing a letter and the answer is yes
Where else would you start for life change personal change? You
don't need a pink package to fall out of the sky
You don't need massive bombard pre-conscious subconscious
practice
Channeling find a 2000-year go guru. I mean you don't need any
of that stuff pass on all that kids are afraid of that stuff
Too much of it you'll be out on a
limb with surely. I mean don't pass on all
This stuff is too easy the steps too
simple, it's called take action number one on neglect
On errors in discipline number two start setting up some
disciplines and if you'll do that, you'll perform a miracle
now
Here's the second part of the miracle number one is do
what you can here's number two do the best you can
If that's not your philosophy, I
would ask you to amend it
Let me give you the best of ancient script
Here's what it says
Whatever your hands find to do do it with all your might
do it with all your strength and do it with all your power
What a good philosophy that kind of philosophy revolutionize
your life if you haven't picked it up lately
a
Guy slips in late company doesn't seem to mind slips out
early first one in the parking lot heading for happy hour
Stretches his break comes early
for lunch late back from lunch
Company doesn't seem to notice guy says
Best as I can calculate I'm putting in about a
half a day's work and I'm collecting a full day's pay
And the guy says I got it
Made little does he know?
The seeds of his own disaster are already being
sown by the weakness of his own personal philosophy
It's not the economy that's going
to determine your next six years
It's your philosophy about labor and about activity
and about miracle and soil and seed and sunshine
And rain and the economy and the banks and the
money and the companies and the schools and what's going on
It's your philosophy and your attitude
and then your ability to take action
all of that
We call the process of life change miracle working
Number one do what you can number two
do the best you can here was number
four
Results
Results every once in a while you got to take a
measure see how you're doing with these three pieces philosophy attitude
activity now we take a measure called results
What is the results at the end of the
day the results at the end of the week?
You can't let too much time go by without checking
When time goes by six years I've been out
there working when I met my teacher mr. Shiloh
Shiloh said well, mr. Rohn, let's just go through a
little summary here. He said in the last six years
How much money have you saved and invested?
Let's go through a little tab list here how much money
have you saved and invested the last six years I said what?
Zero he said you have
Messed up you remember these notes. I like that
You've messed up
he
Said who sold you on that plan. I
Thought my gosh the man's right. I'm
a nice guy. I bought the wrong plan
What if you were 50 and broke
Right didn't need to change countries bought the
wrong plan. What a sad scenario that would be
the chip said these questions let's go through some results
He said how many dollars do you get lost 200 grand a dance with
200 students needed snap down. We have to go through a lot of those
Sort of rules and observe them to get access to sushi income to get
land markets something else taiiiiaut and certain amount of money in Texas the cash to
ifiques support that schön refers to a fineお денег
He said how many books have
you read in the last 90 days?
I said what?
Zero wisdom of the world available
Change your life change your future
Wisdom of the world available develop develop any skill
you want earn the kind of income you want
Have all the treasures you want equities you want relationship
with your family that you want everything that you want available
And the wisdom of the world to help you get it haven't
read any books in the last 90 days. My teacher said mr. Rohn
you have
Messed up i'm telling you you've got the deal
Shove said mr. Rohn in the last six months.
How many classes have you taken to improve your skills?
or to develop new skills
Go for the american dream
Become rich and powerful and
sophisticated and healthy and influential
How many classes have you taken in
the last six months? I said how many?
Zero he said you have
Messed up said you don't need to un-mess the country
You don't need to straighten out the perplexed. You
don't need to straighten out any of this stuff
All you've got to do is look within
And let results teach you
a great deal about your own
activity
your own attitude
and your own philosophy
I went through that process
Take this phrase home results
is the name of the game
What other game is there?
Results
Here's all life asks us to
do make measurable progress in reasonable time
Just take home that little phrase good phrase. We're asked
in life simply to make measurable progress in reasonable time
We demanded of our children, how many years do
you want your child to spend in fourth grade?
Approximately
About
one
If it looks like they're not going to
make it we pour on the pressure call
legitimate pressure lack of results
peer pressure family pressure school pressure community pressure every other kind of pressure
we can bring to bear why you can't stay more than one year in
fourth grade
As parents you'd have to leave the community you say well, what
if they're nice kids wouldn't you give them three or four years?
The answer is no
You got to make better progress than that
So you got to check fairly often
some things you got to check every day
Some things you got to check at
least by the end of the week
You got to make sure you're not throwing away more
money than you have to make in your first year
You're not going to be able to make a bigger
impact than you have to make in your first year
Salesman joins this little sales company
supposed to make 10 calls first week
Wouldn't it be legitimate call him
in on friday and say john what?
How many calls I mean this stuff is simple
John says well say john well won't
fit in this little box here well
Well
Now john starts with a story you say john
I don't need a story
I need what?
a number
A number what will the number tell me?
Everything
John's supposed to make 10 calls. What
if he made 20 you say wow
Wow, we got somebody
What if he only made one call
Whoa
Oh
Will that tell us something about john's philosophy
The answer is yes, will it tell
us something about his attitude, of course
Will it tell us something about his
disciplines, of course, and if he wants
A lesson in life change all he
has to do is be willing to face
the numbers
And come up with the results that will teach you to either
celebrate if you got good results or fix whatever needs to be fixed
in your philosophy
attitude
activity called disciplines
You don't need to go anywhere
else. I do believe in affirmations
They are valuable as long as you affirm the truth
Because it says in ancient scripts the truth
What?
Will set you free
Free to do what amend your errors and pick
up new disciplines. That's what the truth is for
to help us amend our errors
and
Pick up the disciplines for life change. That's what the
truth is for. So I do believe in affirming the truth
If you're broke best thing
to affirm is I am broke
I am
I friend
process of life change and it doesn't
matter how small the process is to start
one discipline starts it and then
one discipline feeds another feeds another
and the first thing you know you've
got this whole cycle in an upward positive
motion and it's called life change
it's called income change it's called health
change relationship with your family
change equities unprecedented that you
can have in numbers that will stagger
the imagination if you do not curse
what's available and start amending what's
possible to get the results that
you want I don't think I can put
it in any better language that's it kids can
do it teenagers can do it parents can
do it managers can do it right government
officials can do it anybody can do
it anybody can do this stuff called
personal change Wow results is the name of the game
success is a numbers game good note to
make success is a numbers game you got
to go for the numbers you
got to understand what the numbers are
you got to understand what the numbers are
how many pounds overweight should you be
at age 50 approximately John says I got
big bones we'll give you 10 pounds
10 pounds for big bones otherwise come on
John 20 pounds 25 pounds shouldn't we turn
on the caution light at work and at
home
home blinking caution light so this is
what's that caution light so John's up
about 20 25 pounds we got the blinking light
going at home got to go in here at
work to remind him what wrong numbers
okay 35 40 pounds red light blinking at
home so he said what's that blinking
red lights John's up about 40 pounds 50
pounds we got the siren
siren sometimes she's unbelievable how you can
do business with a siren at work coming
in and out she wherever she goes she
's like turning the radio on get
up what's up selling Bergo she's like yeah
I need to
listen to herself I need to work mouth
what's the siren at home and at work
How committed are you to taking what's
available and turning it into equities unprecedented
since we live in a country that there's been
no such country in the last six and a half
thousand years.
If you'll pick up that process, ladies
and gentlemen, I'm telling you, it's called life
change of the best order.
Now here's the last one.
Number five is called lifestyle.
Lifestyle is simply learning how to live well.
The last of the five major pieces.
Here's the ultimate challenge of life.
I've worked on this.
You cannot believe how hard since age
25 and that is after applying better philosophy,
attitude and and activity and picking now up results.
What are results for?
Here's my ultimate challenge on results.
To fashion good word to jot down fashion.
Fashion for yourself, lifestyle or
what we call the good life.
That's the ultimate challenge to take your
results, take your money, take your results,
take the return, take the equities you've
gathered and now fashion for yourself a good
life like weaving a tapestry.
And Mr.
Shelf gave me all kinds of examples.
On lifestyle.
He gave me two phrases that helped change my life.
In case you have to leave early,
let me give you these two phrases.
It'll be worth the price
of coming and being here today.
Just take these two phrases home
in case you have to leave early.
Here's number one.
Shelf said, Mr.
Rowan, if you wish to be wealthy, study wealth.
When he said that, I said, my gosh.
I don't know.
No.
I don't know anybody that studies wealth.
Where am I going to learn it?
He said, nevermind Mr. Rowan.
Now that you've met me, if you'll be with
me for a while, he said, and if you'll commit
yourself, he said, I will teach you.
And he taught me.
He taught me the books.
He taught me the stuff.
Changed my life.
By the time I was 31, I was a millionaire.
The man taught me well.
If you wish to be wealthy, study wealth.
If you were to show me your present
economic plan, in a personal conversation between you
and me, you say, Mr. Rowan, let me
disclose for you my current economic financial plan
for the future.
Would I get so excited?
I'd say, hey, I'm going to go
across the country and lecture on your plan.
And if the answer is no, Mr. Rowan, you
probably wouldn't want to go across the country and
lecture on my plan here's my question to
you why not why wouldn't you have a
superior powerful financial plan that's taking you
to the places you want to go
I'm asking you if you find yourself caught
like I was at age 25 make the
personal commitment today and say I'm
gonna study and I'm gonna change and
five years from now nobody's gonna be able
to say how come you don't have a
superior plan living in a
superior country with superior opportunity
nobody's gonna be able to say that five
years from now of me if you'll make that
commitment I'm telling you this will be
one of the most exciting days of your
life not because of my seminar it'll be
life because of your commitment to
this simple little process I've outlined for
you here was the second phrase mr. Shove
said mr. own if you wish to be happy
study happiness
I didn't know happiness was a study
my best hope for happiness at age 25
was to just go through the day with my
fingers crossed open somehow something could make me happy
Shove said no mr. own happiness is
not something you postpone happiness is not
something off in the future happiness is
something you design you've got to get
the word happiness is something you design
happiness is a study happiness is a
practice happiness is an art it's not an
accident it's an art and anybody that
wants to can study practice the art
happy living happiness is like culture
money doesn't make you cultured but
culture is within the grasp of all of
us how much is a book on sophistication in
the marketplace four thousand dollars no forty dollars I'm
telling you in America everything's
available everything's within reach all
you have to be is committed to it
and make it a study culture is a study
sophistication is a study it's not an
amount it's not an account it's a study
money doesn't make you sophisticated and cultured
I know a guy that's rich he's a
Claude the guy's a Claude eats with his
elbow in his soup I mean it's just a
Claude nothing much more pitiful than a rich
Claude I mean you know it's a sad
thing to see money doesn't make
you sophisticated only study and practice
makes you sophisticated only study and
practice makes you culture and only
study and practice makes you happy
study and practice makes you rich key
phrase don't be lazy and learning one how
to do well next how to live well
don't be lazy and learning
and practicing the art of economics
practicing the art of productivity and practicing the art of
lifestyle. Shoaff taught me in such simple
terms. Shoaff said, Mr. Owen, if you're
getting your shoes shined, shoe shine boy
has done an exceptional job. You look down,
you got one of the world's all-time
great shines and you pay him. Now you've
got a little change in your hand.
Question pops in your mind, should I give
him one quarter or two quarters as a
tip from a neat shine? Here's what Shoaff said,
if two amounts pop in your mind always
go for the higher amount and become the
higher thinking person. That helped change
my life. Here's what he said, become
a two-quarter person. Now you can tell that
was a long time ago when a quarter
was a good tip. Now it takes
dollars but just substitute 1992 dollars for
quarters.
Shoaff said, hey if you, you know, are
thinking one quarter or two quarters and you say,
well no I'll just give him one quarter.
He said, that'll affect you the rest of
the day. The rest of the day you'll
look down, see this great shine, you'll say I
got to be really cheap, one lousy quarter
tip from a shine. But he said, if you'll
go for the two quarters, Shoaff said,
you can't believe the extra happiness you
can buy for just an extra quarter.
That's called studying and practicing the art
of lifestyle which means living well.
Money doesn't make you happy. Father wads up
a twenty dollar bill, throws it at his son.
And says, if you need the darn stuff that
bad, take it, just get out of my face.
How sad, a father with money and no
joy. He studied economics but he never studied
joy. I'm asking you to turn that around.
Turn that all around. I did a seminar one
time.
St. Louis, Missouri. When I finished a
seminar like this, man walked up and said,
Mr. Owen, you've really gotten to me.
Said, I'm gonna change my philosophy, I'm
gonna change my attitude, I'm gonna
change my life, I'm gonna change
everything. He said, you've touched me today.
And he said, you'll hear about me.
You'll hear my story someday. I said, okay.
Right, a lot of people, right, say things.
Sure enough, a few months later, I come
back to St. Louis, did another seminar. When I
finished my seminar, I saw this man
come walking up. I didn't remember his name,
but he said, I'm sure you'll remember me
as the man who said, I'm gonna go make
some changes. You've touched me today. I
said, I do remember you. He said, I'm
telling you things are already happening for
me. I cannot believe in just a matter
of months. He said, one of the
things I decided to change was my relationship
with my family. He said, my wife
and I have two lovely teenage daughters. Parents
couldn't ask for any more beautiful
lovely daughters. And he said, I'm the
only one that's given him trouble.
He said these daughters of ours
have never given us any trouble
He said I've usually been the one all these
years given all the trouble and all the static
He said my daughters love to go to the rock concerts and
I'm always giving them trouble. They have to beg me for the money
Said I don't want you to
go you stay out too late
Music's too loud
You're gonna ruin your hearing won't be
able to hear the rest of your life
And he said I just get on their
case and he said they keep begging keep begging
Finally when they beg long enough, I say all right. Here's
the money if you have to go that bad just go
I said, that's how I've been up until now
But he said after I left your seminar, I
decided to change all that called lifestyle living. Well
He said you won't believe it not long ago. I picked
up the newspaper and I saw an advertisement and I knew
My two daughters. It was one of
their favorite performers was coming to town
He said guess what I did. He said
I went down and bought the tickets myself
and
Brought him home put him in an envelope
And when I saw my daughters later that day
He said I handed them this envelope
and I said to my two lovely daughters
You may not believe it but inside
this envelope are two tickets for the upcoming
concert they could not
believe and
He also added you'll be happy to know
Begging days are over
Now they cannot
leave
He said now don't open the
envelope till you get to the concert
They said okay
So they go to the concert come concert time
Open up the envelope hand the tickets to the usher. He says
follow me and he starts down front the girls say hey, hold it
Hold it something must be wrong
He takes another look says no
nothing's wrong. Follow me 10th row Center
Now they cannot
leave
10th row Center
The only tickets they were able able
you never to beg for was right
third balcony can't see
He said I stayed up a little
late that night sure enough little after midnight
My two daughters come bursting through the front
door one of them lands in my lap
The other ones got her arms around my neck. They're both
saying you got to be one of the all-time world's great fathers
He said mr. Owen you're right.
I can't believe same money different father
he said Mr. Owen you're right
He said I've started making the changes and
I decided to start with my teenagers my girls
He said what a difference it's making in my life
And I'm telling you you can do that with
your lifestyle. You can do it with your sales career
You can do it with your management career. You can do it
with any part of your life if you're looking for equities unmatched
Do not curse the only thing you have don't complain about the only
thing you have which is seed and soil sunshine rain miracle and seasons
but start changing and processing and
Evaluating things like we're covering today and this
process of change will take off for you
You will not believe what can
happen in such a short period
Next subject personal development
Personal Development
percentile
ouble
Personal development
ták
that that was difficult for me to give
up that was quite a transition for me to
make and blaming myself but mr.
Schultz started out with something very very
important let me give that to you
he said it's not what happens that
determines the major part of your future
it's not what happens what happens happens
to us all said the key is what
you do about it it's not what
happens it's what you do about it
and he said if you will start
that process of change do something different
the next 90 days than you did the
last 90 days like picking up the books to
read do something different like
the new health disciplines relationship with
your family whatever it is doesn't matter
how small it is if you'll start
doing different things with the same circumstances
once this it's happening you're going to enjoy
the future as it is by the way
I got to the technique with
Mark Be mayor from Commercial Organization της
in City College they have a
volatile energy management approach that some
say functioning oh how's that Thousand
tries to get things in the past
seemed like a secret
how does that feel around it
that was an important lesson
for Mk relationship with Lou principles
psychology recipes risks second theory since
artists Doug Rogan I just I don't
know if I will teach the摁 attempt
you see he taught something that I haven't
seen no he said when you ask me to
do take on the sample that you got an 뜨mer
Now, sometimes it's a little tough to
take, blaming yourself instead of the marketplace.
Taking responsibility instead of putting
it off on someone else.
That transition sometimes is a challenging mission.
And this one was a little tough for me.
So let's talk a little bit about personal development.
That extraordinary adventure I undertook starting at age 25.
And I've never ceased that adventure.
I'm still going for it in the 90s.
I want to get better and better.
I want my craft to get better, my business operations
to get better, the things I do to get better.
Because once I picked up the simple formula, I'm telling you, it's easy
to figure out where the problem is if you go to work on it.
Now, let's talk about personal development.
And in helping kids understand personal
development, I always start with money.
Now, money is not the only place to start.
Money certainly isn't the only value,
but we've all got to start somewhere.
Money is something you can count.
Kids are interested in money.
A lot of things are a little tougher to measure.
But economics is pretty easy, right?
Because you can count.
Somebody says, how are you doing?
I don't know.
Let's count.
Now, this is not the only count.
I understand that.
There's a lot of other things to count.
But to see if there may be some errors in your judgment and
lack of disciplines in your life, we might as well start with money.
Because it's so easy.
It's easy to count.
So let's just start there and see
whether or not maybe we have messed up.
Okay.
So here's how I explain it to kids.
We get paid for bringing value to the marketplace.
Key to understanding economics.
Marketplace is also described as reality.
Okay.
Reality, the marketplace.
Now, it takes time.
It takes time to bring value to the marketplace.
But we don't get paid for time.
It's very important for kids
to understand as well as adults.
We don't get paid for time.
Mistakenly, the man says, well, I'm
making about $20 for an hour.
Not true.
If that was true, you could just
stay home, have them send your money.
No, it's not true.
You don't get paid for the hour.
You get paid for the hour.
You get paid for the
value you put in the time.
So we don't get paid for time.
We get paid for value.
Now, since that's true, here's one
of the key questions of the afternoon.
Is it possible to become twice as valuable and
make twice as much money in the same time?
Is it possible to become three times as valuable as you now
are and make three times as much money in the same time?
Is it possible?
Of course.
If you want to really emphasize
something, that's a good phrase to it.
Of course.
Okay.
Now, all you have to do to earn more
money in the same time is simply become more valuable.
America is unique.
It's a ladder to climb.
It starts down here, what?
About $4 an hour?
Big argument last year in Congress about the starting place.
Should be five, should be five, should be five.
Well, no, it doesn't need to be five.
Why not start with four?
It's a ladder.
Right.
This is not a bed.
This is a ladder.
It's a ladder to climb.
Starts at $4.
Now, somebody said, well, should be five, should be five.
Well, maybe.
If you're going to stay at the bottom for
the rest of your life, it probably should be five.
But that's kind of a pitiful way to live.
Start and not grow.
Start and not change.
Start and not become more valuable.
Hey, the whole scenario of life
is to start number one and what?
Become more valuable number two.
So America is a ladder to climb.
Starts at $4 an hour.
And the more valuable you become,
you just keep moving up the ladder.
Top income last year, what?
$52 million?
Guy that runs Disney?
Would a company pay somebody
for one year's work $52 million?
And the answer is, of course.
This is one of those of course places.
Of course.
If you help a company make a
billion dollars, would they pay you $52 million?
The answer is, of course.
It's chicken feed.
I mean, it's not much money.
Now, why that much money?
Because he has become so valuable.
Now, why would we pay somebody only $4 an hour?
They're not very valuable to the marketplace.
Now, we got to make that distinction to the marketplace.
Might be a valuable brother, a valuable member
of the community, valuable member of the church,
valuable member in the sight
of God, to the human family.
Of course, those kind of values.
But to the marketplace, which is called what?
Reality.
Reality is if you're not very
valuable, you don't get much money.
Those are called the facts.
I mean, that's how that is.
Well, then how do you get more money?
Simple answer.
Somebody says, well, I'll go on strike for more.
Well, here's a major problem with that.
Here's a major problem with that.
You can't get rich by demand.
Somebody says, well, I'm waiting for a raise.
I'm telling you, it's easier to
climb than to wait for a raise.
Why not just become more valuable rather than wait?
I'm telling you, that's the key to all good things.
Becoming more valuable.
Why would we pay somebody $400?
Why would we pay somebody $500 an hour?
They've become more valuable to the marketplace.
See how this works?
I'm telling you, this stuff is so easy.
This is America.
This is a ladder.
How far is it from four to five?
I'm telling you, it's not far.
Four to $5 an hour?
If you work for McDonald's, haul out
the trash, they'll pay you $5 an hour.
If you whistle while you haul out the trash,
they'll pay you $5 an hour.
I'm telling you, you'll get an
extra dollar just for a good attitude.
Yay, McDonald's.
Wear the hat.
Incredible.
And then you just keep becoming
more valuable, more valuable, more valuable.
I got a telephone call five years ago.
The company said, we're ready to expand internationally.
We need some help.
I was sort of semi-retired.
Looking for the next exotic beach.
They said, no, no, Mr. Rohn.
We got a project for you.
Right.
We're going to expand internationally.
We could use your help.
Next little while, we'll add some millions
to your fortune, make it worth your while.
I said, okay.
I thought later, isn't that interesting that they called me?
My second thought was, of course they'd call me.
Who else would they call?
I mean, you know, I can get the job done.
Now, how come?
How come I got a telephone call worth millions?
I had become valuable.
Now I'm a farm boy from Idaho.
I was raised in obscurity.
One year of college and
I thought I was thoroughly educated.
Made all kinds of mistakes galore.
At age 25, the creditors are calling me saying,
hey, you told us the check was in the mail.
I got pennies in my pocket.
I got nothing in the bank.
I'm behind on my promises.
How come I get a telephone call
five years ago and it's worth millions?
I changed.
I turned my life around.
Is it possible to become worth millions?
Speaking economically, now there's a lot of
values to become, but let's just talk economics.
Is it possible to become that valuable?
And the answer is, of course, of course.
Now, let me give you the secret.
Shoaff said, here's the secret, Mr. Rohn.
Learn to work harder on yourself
than you do on your job.
Once I got that, it turned my life around.
Learn to work harder on yourself.
Learn to work harder on yourself
than you do on your job.
He said, if you work hard
on your job, you'll make a living.
If you work hard on
yourself, you can make a fortune.
If you would have known me at age 25,
you would have said, Jim Rohn's a hard worker.
If you'd have known me, you'd have said that.
I'm the guy.
I don't mind coming a little
bit early, staying a little bit longer.
I'm the guy.
I don't mind coming a little
bit early, staying a little bit late.
I don't mind that.
You'd have said, well, Jim Rohn's a hard worker.
You say, well, how come he's got pennies
in his pocket, nothing in the bank and behind
on his promises?
Well, I was a hard worker, but I was
working hard on my job, not on my self.
I'm telling you, if you'll learn that
simple little principle and start the process today,
latest tomorrow, I'll give you tonight to
think it over, and start this whole process
of personal development.
on yourself make yourself more valuable
to the marketplace I'm telling you you
can so dynamically change your income and
economics is the least of the values
that you can start earning in terms
of equity if you'll start working harder on
yourself than you do on your job
work hard on yourself and develop the skills
work hard on yourself and develop the
graces all of the stuff necessary to
become more valuable to the marketplace
I'm telling you your whole life can
explode into change promotions no
problem becoming more valuable to the
company I'm telling you no problem
money no problem economics no problem future
no problem if you just go to work on
the right thing not get things out there to
change don't try to change the seed
don't change the soil don't change the
sunshine don't change the rain don't
change the mix of seasons let the
miracle of everything that's available work
for you and start working on the
inside work on your philosophy work
on your attitude work on your personality
work on your personality work on your
values work on your character work on your
abilities and if you'll start making
those personal changes I'm telling you
everything will change for you now let
me give you another scenario on personal
development it's called the four major lessons
in life to learn before we get
to the four major lessons in life to
learn let me give you a key phrase for
your notes here it is life and business
is like the seasons life and business is
like the seasons
and then you say I'm going to make
a profit by making a profit by making a
Frank Sinatra sings, life is like the seasons.
Now here's one of the
key phrases that changed my life.
Starting at age 25, you can see this whole scenario.
Personal development for me began.
I've never been the same since.
Here's the next key phrase.
You cannot change the seasons.
But you can change yourself.
You can't change the seasons.
My best hope, right?
When I'm 25 years old, my best hope was
to go through the day with my fingers crossed saying,
I sure hope things will change.
It seemed to be my only way for
my life to get better if things would change.
Here's what I discovered.
It isn't going to change.
I did a second.
I did a seminar one time for
Standard Oil executives and management in Honolulu,
now known as Chevron.
And we're talking economics one
day around the conference table.
And one of them said to me, Mr. Rohn,
you know some fairly important people around the world.
You have a chance to travel internationally.
Can you tell us what you think
the 80s are going to be like?
You can tell how far back this goes.
He said, what do you think
the 80s are going to be like?
And I thought for a moment and I said, gentlemen,
I do know the right people
and I do have some experience.
I think I can tell you.
So they all leaned in a little closer and I said, gentlemen, based
on the people I know and based on the best of my own experience,
I think in the 80s, it's going
to be about like it's always been.
Aren't you glad you came today?
I mean, that's inside stuff.
I don't just spread that around everywhere.
It's going to be about like it's always been.
It isn't going to change to hope that it'll change.
It's called whistling in the wind.
Being so naive, hoping for
something that isn't going to occur.
I can give you the shortest history
lesson that you can imagine in one sentence.
What describes human history on the spinning planet
the last six and a half thousand years?
Let me describe it for you in one sentence.
Here's human history in one sentence.
Opportunity mixed with difficulty.
That's about as simple as you can put it.
And opportunity mixed with difficulty isn't going to change.
The man says, well, if it isn't going to change for
the future, if it isn't going to change in the 90s,
how will my life ever change?
Answer, when you change.
And if you will change, everything will change for you.
Your bank account will change.
Your income will change.
Your future will change.
The ability to acquire your dreams will change.
It'll all change if you will change.
And now let's go through the scenario of the seasons.
Life and business is like the seasons.
Let's cover them.
Here's number one major lesson in life to learn.
Learn how to have a good life.
Learn how to handle the winters.
You say, well, Mr. Rohn, a
lot of this stuff is fairly obvious.
That's true.
Just need somebody like me just
to come along and remind us.
This is what this is called today, a reminding session.
I got no new truth for you to discover.
This is all old stuff.
We just need to hear it again.
Somebody get on our case a little bit, right?
We all need that.
Here's number one lesson.
Learn how to handle the winters.
That's obvious.
The winters come right after falls.
And pray tell how often.
Every year, according to written history, for
the last six and a half thousand.
To cross your fingers and say, I
hope, I hope, I hope it doesn't come.
I'm telling you, we call that naive.
Now, there's all kinds of winters.
Not just the winter of the season.
But there's all kinds of winters.
Wintertime.
The downtime.
The discouraging time.
One writer called it the winter of discontent.
The winter when you can't figure it out.
The winter when it all goes wrong.
Economic winters, social winters,
political winters, and personal winters.
When your heart is smashed in a thousand pieces.
The nights are unusually long.
It's called wintertime.
Barbra Streisand sings, it used to
be so natural to talk about forever.
But used to be's don't count anymore.
They just lay on the floor.
Till we sweep the floor.
We sweep them away.
You don't sing me love songs.
You don't say you need me.
And you don't bring me flowers anymore.
A song of winter.
But hey, we're acquainted with all those winter scenarios.
We've been through them all.
Now the question is, what
do you do about the winters?
Well, you can't get rid of
January by tearing it off the calendar.
But here's what you can do
with the upcoming winters of your life.
The long ones.
The short ones.
The easy ones.
The more difficult ones.
Here's what you can do.
Get wiser and stronger and better.
Just make a list of that trio of good words.
Wiser, stronger, and better.
To challenge for yourself the upcoming winters of your life.
Don't you think you could read more?
Pick up the scenario.
Pick up the books.
Pick up the cassettes.
Why don't you put some stuff on
cassettes so you can listen to it.
Put it in books so you can read it.
Now putting it on video so you can see it.
I'm telling you.
Anybody that wants to can get wise.
Next is stronger.
Anybody can get stronger.
If you're willing to do
the push-ups, you can get stronger.
If you're willing to put yourself
through the paces, you can get stronger.
Can you develop stronger skills?
And the answer is yes.
Start practicing, practicing, practicing.
And you can get stronger.
Can you get stronger in handling life situations?
Of course.
But you've got to go to work on yourself.
You can't blame out there wishing it was easier.
Wish you were stronger.
And here's the last one.
Get better.
Anybody can get better.
Language, we can all get better.
I've been lecturing now for 33 years and I'm
telling you today versus 33 years ago, I'm better.
First time I gave a talk, I
stood up, my mind sat back down.
I mean, you know, I've been through that whole deal.
Opened my mouth, nothing came out for a while.
My knees are banging together,
the sweat's pouring off my face.
I'm shaking like a leaf.
It's called terror.
In case you haven't tried it.
Those first attempts.
But I'm telling you, I got through it and I
did it again and I got through it and I
did it again and I got through it.
And now, of course, I can lecture
for a few hours in one day.
Anybody can get better.
Develop the skills.
Okay?
Handle the upcoming winters.
Don't wish away the winters.
That's called naive.
Wish for the skills.
Wish for the strength.
Wish for the wisdom.
Here's the second major lesson in life to learn.
Learn how to take advantage of the spring.
Uniquely enough, spring follows winter.
And pray tell how often?
Six and a half thousand times.
I mean, those are good odds.
I'd gamble on it one more time.
Every time.
You can't beat those odds.
I'm telling you.
Spring is called opportunity.
Another day is called opportunity.
Days follow nights.
How about that?
And how often?
Every day.
But now here's what we
must learn to do with opportunity.
Underline two strategic words in that sentence.
Take advantage.
Just because spring comes is no sign
you're going to look good in the fall.
You've got to take advantage of it.
You've got to do something with it.
Read every book you can on
what to do with your springs.
What to do with your opportunities.
What to do with your days.
What to do with your chances.
Don't miss the educational process.
Don't miss the process of learning.
To understand opportunity keeps coming.
But the key is taking advantage.
Taking advantage.
Everybody in this room has got to
learn to do one of two things.
Plant in the spring or beg in the fall.
And it doesn't mean you can't do it.
And it doesn't mean you can't become a sophisticated beggar.
But you don't need the reputation.
Learn to plant in the spring.
Take advantage.
And there's an urgency here on
springtime because there's just a few springs,
handful of springs offered to each of us.
So take advantage swiftly and quickly.
Don't just let the time pass.
The Beatles wrote, life is very short.
And for John Lennon it was extra short.
For Michael Landon it was extra short.
But life is short.
At the longest it's short.
So don't just let the springs pass, pass, pass.
Take advantage.
Seize the day.
Seize the moment.
Seize the opportunity.
That's the key.
Springtime.
Life is fragile.
Life is brief.
Elton John sings, she lived her life like a candle.
In the wind.
It's fragile.
It's brief.
Whatever you're going to do,
you got to get at it.
Don't just let it pass away.
Here's major lesson number three.
In the summer, learn how to nourish and protect.
We've got two challenges in the summer.
In the personal development part of our life.
And that is become capable.
And powerful enough in the summer.
And wise enough in the summer.
To nourish what's good.
And defend yourself against what's bad.
Nourish and defend.
The summertime is an interesting time.
It holds the possibility of the promise of harvest time.
But it also has the possibility of the threat.
Sure enough, as soon as you planted your garden.
The busy bugs and the noxious
weeds are out to take it.
And let me give you another word of advice.
They will take it.
Unless you prevent it.
Summertime is an interesting time.
Best as I can describe summertime.
You got to nourish your values like a mother.
Nourish like a mother.
Go after the threat to the
values you've got like a father.
Deal with the weeds.
Kill the weeds.
Nourish the garden and kill the weeds.
That's called summertime.
What a challenging time.
Give life like a mother.
Take life like a father.
Summertime.
You got to deal with the
negative as well as the positive.
Summertime is a unique complex mix of positive and negative.
Opportunity and threat.
What a scenario of life itself.
Opportunity and threat to the opportunity.
And you got to deal with both.
You got to think positive
and you got to think negative.
You got to deal with both.
You got to handle what's ever out to threaten you.
You got to learn to threaten it back.
Summertime.
Interesting time.
Nourish like a mother.
Defend like a father.
You got to be like
your blood stream in the summer.
Red corpuscles to what?
Nourish.
White corpuscles to what?
Fight.
You got to both nourish and fight.
You got to nourish and be vigilant.
Okay.
White corpuscles.
You got to think negative.
You can't just think positive.
We call you naive.
Somebody says, well, I've been taught to be all positive.
You'll be some kind of freak.
You can't be all positive.
Thank God for white corpuscles that think negative all day.
Guess what white corpuscles are looking for all day?
Problems.
Infection.
White corpuscles say, just show me some infection.
I'll kill it.
Why?
Because I'm a man.
It's out to kill the body.
It's out to kill our chances.
It's out to kill our future.
Whatever threatens us, we threaten.
I'm asking you to take sword to your enemies.
Whatever's out to threaten you, threaten your
health, you got to threaten it back.
Like white corpuscles.
Kill what's evil.
Nourish what's good.
Love like a mother.
Hate like a father.
Father says to whatever threatens his family, take
two or three more steps toward this family
and threaten my family.
You'll cease to exist.
I'm father.
I kill.
I'm a father.
Don't let the weeds take your garden.
Wreck your chances for a good harvest.
Deal with your enemies in the summer.
Called good and evil.
The great struggle in life is
called good and evil, tyranny and liberty.
Sickness and health.
That's the way life is.
Tyranny threatens liberty.
over Kuwait. Can't have that. If tyranny takes
Kuwait, it'll take Saudi Arabia. If it takes
Saudi Arabia, it'll take something else. Where are
we going to stop tyranny? As soon as possible,
lest it take the whole world value. So George
Bush draws a line in the sand, consults with
his allies, sends a half a million troops
to Saudi Arabia. Finally, desert sword, desert storm
takes on Saddam Hussein, drives him out of Kuwait.
Why? Because it has to be done. The great struggle
between liberty and tyranny, the great struggle between
evil and good. And you've got to treat
your own life the same. Says Saddam Hussein,
you can't have Kuwait, can't have Saudi Arabia.
Furthermore, we're going to kick you
out. Hires Chief White Corpuscle General Schwarzkopf.
Takes care of the matter. I'm asking
you in the summer, nourish like a mother,
threaten whatever threatens you like a father. Now
you can also turn around the scenario. That's true.
Love like a father, hate like a mother.
Give life like a father, take life like
a mother. You can turn the scenario around.
The key is both love and hate.
Single parents have got the greatest challenge.
Love like a mother, hate like a father.
Love like a father, hate like a mother.
Nothing more dangerous than an angry mother.
Beware the female species of the animal.
They call her black widow spider.
Why? Because when she finishes, there is no male spider.
I saw this article.
I was flying on an airplane up in Canada.
I saw this article in one of the airplane magazines.
Showed a picture of this guy with his shirt off,
these claw marks down his back, teeth marks in his neck.
The guy almost got killed. He was out in
the woods. Saw a mama bear with her little cub.
Said, oh, this looks cute.
Had his flash camera, went flash flash, took a picture.
Mama bear treats it unkindly.
Promptly chases him.
Caught him. Almost killed him before they got to him.
Beware a mama bear.
So, love like a father, hate like a mother.
However you want to treat this scenario.
It's very important.
It's called summer time.
Part of the personal development challenge is to be challenged to
learn to nourish all of the things that are important to you.
It's called summer time.
Learn to nourish all of your values.
From a garden, to a family relationship, to
a love affair, to a marriage, to a business.
Anything that's valuable to you called equity.
You've got to nourish it. You've got to
feed it. You've got to take care of it.
But you've also got to defend it.
It's called the way things are.
Key.
In the summer.
Now here's number four.
Fourth major lesson in life to learn.
In the fall, in the harvest.
Learn to reap in the harvest.
Without complaint.
Important part of personal development.
Reap in the harvest without complaint.
Take full responsibility.
Once you've learned this scenario.
It's not the seed.
It's not the soil.
It's not the sunshine.
It's not the rain.
It's not the miracle of the giving of life.
It's not the seasons that's to be criticized.
We must take personal responsibility.
So in the harvest.
In the summer.
Take personal responsibility.
It's your crop.
Whatever you've reaped. It's your crop.
Take responsibility.
No complaint.
And here's the next one. No apology.
The best of human maturity is
no apology if you've done well.
And no complaint if you haven't.
Knowing that that's where the answers lie.
Within.
And then without in the miracle of
the possibilities that we have to work with.
Those are the four major lessons in life to learn.
Let's talk about some more parts of personal development.
Here's the first one.
Physical.
The physical side.
Gotta take care of yourself.
Do not neglect to take care of yourself.
Good phraseology used in the Bible.
In my amateur way.
But let me put it to you best I can.
Here's what it says.
Treat your body like a temple.
That's a good phrase.
Good suggestion.
A temple meaning something you take extremely good care of.
A temple.
That's a good phrase.
Treat your body like a temple.
Not a woodshed.
A temple.
Take good care.
It's the only place you've got to live currently.
The temple.
Nutrition.
My mother studied nutrition.
Passed it along to me.
Passed it along to my father.
My children.
My grandchildren.
What a legacy that was.
Learning to just take care of your stuff.
Key phrase.
Some people don't do well because they don't feel well.
They've got the gifts.
They've got the skills.
Maybe they just haven't taken care of themselves.
They don't have the vitality.
Key phrase.
Vitality is a major part of success.
Vitality.
So take care of yourself.
I know a guy that raises race horses.
I'm telling you the guy feeds
his horses better than he feeds himself.
He's so careful how he feeds his horses.
He's so careful what they eat.
He's so careful that they get everything.
And because of that extreme care.
I mean these are magnificent animals.
They can run like the wind.
But you ought to see this guy.
Ten steps up a flight of stairs
and I mean he's all out of breath.
His horses can run like the wind and
he can hardly make it up the steps.
The guy takes care of his animals
better than he takes care of himself.
Some people feed their dogs
better than they feed their kids.
Physical.
Now there's all kinds of parts to physical.
Here's one.
Appearance is part of the physical.
Never have a second chance to make a first impression.
The physical side.
And here's some of the best
advice on appearance I can give you.
Comes from ancient script again.
It says God looks on the inside.
People look on the outside.
Isn't that?
Good information.
Now you say well people shouldn't
judge you by how you look.
Well let me give you a clue.
They do.
You can't deal in these shoulds and shouldn'ts.
You'll be tipped over the rest of your life.
Now of course when people get to know you.
They'll judge you by more than what they see.
But at first they're gonna take a look.
Okay.
So.
Here's the best advice I can give you.
Make sure the outside is a
major reflection of what's going on inside.
The physical side.
Few minutes a day.
Stay healthy.
Little bit of study on nutrition.
Keep.
Now here's the next part of personal development.
The spiritual part.
I do happen to believe that human beings
are more than just an advanced life form.
An advanced species of the animal kingdom.
I do believe humans are a special creation.
That's just my personal belief.
And I don't ask you to buy it.
But here's what I do ask you to buy.
If you do believe in spirituality in any manner.
Here's my best advice.
Study it and practice it.
Do not neglect your values.
Do not neglect your virtues.
If you do believe in spirituality.
My advice is study it and practice it.
Don't let it go unstudied.
Don't let it go unnourished.
If you do believe.
That's my best advice on the spiritual side.
Now here's the third part.
The mental side.
Part of this personal development
challenge is to develop mentally.
Learn to be a good person.
Learn, study, grow, change.
It's what schooling is all about.
And the human development takes time.
Incredible amounts of time.
That's why we've taken the time for this seminar.
It just takes time.
Some things you can't cover in a 20 minute speech.
You can't cover in a little 5 minute talk.
It takes time.
For humans it takes seem like
more time than any other life form.
For human beings.
The little wildebeest.
In athletes.
In Africa.
Guess how much time it's
got as soon as it's born.
To be able to run with the pack.
So it doesn't get eaten by the lions.
Guess how much time it's got.
A few minutes.
As soon as the little wildebeest is born.
Tries to stand up.
Falls down.
Its mother nudges it.
Gets it to stand back up.
Falls back down.
Finally on little shaky legs.
You've got to get nurse now.
You've got to develop some strength now.
The lions. The lions. The lions.
Falls down.
Gets back up.
Tries to nurse. Mother pushes it away.
No. You've got to get these legs strong.
How much time have we got?
Not much time.
Mama wildebeest says. Not much time.
Not hours.
Not days.
Minutes.
Wow.
But the human baby. Wow.
After 16 years we're not sure.
Unbelievable amount of time it takes.
So it does take time.
For personal development.
It does take time for spiritual development.
Physical development.
But here's also what takes time.
And that's your mental development.
Feeding the mind.
Nourishing the mind.
Some people read so little
they got rickets of the mind.
They couldn't give you a good strong
argument as to their own personal beliefs.
Here's one of the challenges we've got as parents.
And that is to get our kids ready
to debate the major life issues of the 90s.
They've got to get ready to debate.
We've spent this last couple of decades debating communism.
Communism taught capital belongs in the hands of the state.
We've been teaching, no, capital belongs
in the hands of the people.
Communism taught.
People are too dumb and stupid
to know what to do with capital.
You've got to take capital away
from all the dumb, stupid people.
And give it to the all-knowing, all-wise state.
And let the state run everything and let
the people meekly show up for their work assignment.
All glory to the state, communism taught.
The kid says, well, is that all right?
Well, it's not.
It's not.
Is that right?
No.
All glory to the people.
Let the state be the servant of its people.
Not the people be the servant of the state.
I'm telling you, you've got to
be able to pick up those ideologies.
You've got to be able to pick up the philosophy.
And here's the next part.
You've got to be able to defend it.
If you can't defend your virtues and if you can't defend your values, I'm telling you,
even in the 90s, you'll fall prey to philosophies that are not in your best interest.
And we've got to help that.
We've got to help our teenagers.
We've got to help our kids, especially, to be able to debate the major life issues, the political issues and the social issues and the religious issues and the spiritual
issues and the nutritional issues and the economic issues and all of the rest of the issues that are valuable for us to build the kind of equities we want.
You've got to get yourself ready.
And one of the ways you've got to get
ready is not just physical and not just spiritual.
You've got to get ready mentally.
And this is where Shouf went to work on me.
To be ready mentally.
To develop a mind.
To develop a philosophy and also be
able to defend your virtues and your values.
Let's go through it.
You need a good library.
Shouf got me started on my library.
Here's one of the books he recommended.
Think and Grow Rich.
By Napoleon Hill.
Shouf said to me,
Doesn't that book and title intrigue you?
Think and Grow Rich.
Don't you have to read that book?
I said, Yes, sir.
By Napoleon Hill.
I went and found that book in a used bookstore.
That's where I had to start.
In a used bookstore.
I paid less than 50 cents for it.
I've still got it.
It's one of the rare hardback covers.
Think and Grow Rich by Napoleon Hill.
Wow, Shouf was right.
Get a library started. It'll change your life.
Any home over $200,000 has got a library.
Why do you suppose that is?
Wouldn't that make you curious?
How come every home over $200,000 has got a library?
Does that tell you something?
Does that educate you at all?
You say, Well, I can't afford a $200,000 home.
It doesn't matter what size home.
Take your present apartment.
Clean out a car.
Clean out a house.
Clean out a closet.
Call it your library.
And start acting intelligent.
And start this process like I did.
Start developing a library.
Here's what your library needs to show.
That you're a serious student
of health and life,
spirituality, culture,
uniqueness, sophistication,
economics, prosperity,
productivity, sales, management,
skills, values of all kinds.
Let your library show
you're a serious student.
Don't be casual in learning.
Don't be lazy in learning.
Information is the key.
Learning is the beginning of wealth.
Learning is the beginning of health.
Learning is the beginning of prosperity.
Learning is the beginning of democracy.
The beginning of freedom.
All values, all virtues
start with the learning process.
So don't be lazy in learning.
Don't be lazy in gathering the library
that'll teach you and instruct you.
And I got that book, Think and Grow Rich.
Some of the ideas in that book
inspired me no end.
Helped me to change my life.
Now it's got some weird stuff in it.
You know, it's got some weird stuff.
Napoleon was weird.
So you gotta separate out
a little of this weird stuff.
But you can do that.
You can separate out the weird stuff.
Unless you're weird, just do the weird stuff.
Anyway.
Remember, don't be a follower.
Be a student.
That's the key to all books.
Don't be a follower. Be a student.
Okay.
Another book he recommended.
Helped me become financially independent.
We're gonna cover that before we finish this afternoon.
The book was entitled
The Richest Man in Babylon.
By George.
George was a rich man.
He was a rich man.
Claeson. C-L-A-S-O-N.
This little book,
The Richest Man in Babylon.
I use it as a textbook teaching
teenagers how to be rich by 40.
Living in America.
35 if you're extra bright.
Much sooner if you find a unique opportunity.
I got rich by the time I was 31.
Didn't wake till 35.
If you find a unique opportunity.
So we'll get into that.
After we come back from our next break.
Richest Man in Babylon.
Get your library started.
What do you need to put in your library?
Called mental food.
In fact we call it food for?
Thought.
So important to nourish the mind.
Not just the body but nourish the mind.
Key phrase.
Now it needs to be well balanced.
You can't live on mental candy.
Somebody says, well I just read this positive stuff.
That's too second grade.
You gotta get out of second grade.
You can't just be inspired.
You gotta be talked.
You gotta be educated.
Key.
Here's a good book.
It's called How to Read a Book.
Good title.
How to Read a Book by Mortimer Adler.
In this book,
How to Read a Book.
Mortimer you know is the chief
editor of the
new Encyclopedia Britannica.
A good set of books
right to have in your library.
Encyclopedia Britannica.
Chief editor.
Mortimer Adler.
He's still in his 80s.
He's still active, still writing books.
I've got several of his books.
The Six Great Ideas.
A lot of books. Mortimer Adler.
But he wrote this book, How to Read a Book.
Now in this book, How to Read a Book.
Not only does he give you some good suggestions
on how to get the most out of a book.
He'll give you some techniques on how
to get the best out of a book.
Very good.
But here's what's also in his
book, How to Read a Book.
A list of what he calls the best
writings ever written.
The best writings ever written.
I've used it as a centerpiece
for my library.
So I'm just asking you
take a look. If it suits you, fine.
If it doesn't suit you, hey, keep looking
until you find something to suit you.
But well balanced.
Let me give you some of that balance.
Number one, history.
We've all got to have a sense of history.
American history.
National history. International history.
Family history.
Political history.
We all need a sense of history.
Shortest history lesson.
Opportunity mixed with difficulty.
No matter how far back you go.
A thousand years ago.
Two thousand years ago. Three
thousand. Four thousand years ago.
I'm telling you, it all reads the same.
Once you understand the thread
that it isn't going to change,
what's going to change for my life?
Answer. Looks like I'm going to have to change.
History helps us to understand
how it is.
What there is to work with. Seed, soil,
sunshine, rain. And what human beings
have done with it in the past.
And how many of them
have, like I did by age 25,
they have
messed up.
That's what history's for.
Be a good student of history. Here's a good book.
Lessons of History by Durant.
Lessons of History.
by Durant.
This little book is only a hundred pages,
but I'm telling you it's so well written you'll be
intrigued as I was.
This little book, Lessons of History by Durant.
Next is philosophy.
Durant also wrote a good book on
philosophy.
The Story of Philosophy.
It's got a good rundown of the key philosophers
of the last several
years. What they taught and some of the
lives they lived.
You might find it a little difficult, but hey,
you can't just read the easy stuff.
Key phrase to
add here in parenthesis, don't just read
the easy stuff. You won't grow.
You won't change. You won't
develop.
Tackle the more difficult stuff.
Next, novels.
Novels are good.
Sometimes an intriguing story keeps our attention
so that the author can weave in
the philosophy he or she is trying
to get across.
Anne Rand was probably better at that than anybody else
I could possibly think of.
Atlas Shrugged, some of those towering novels.
The novel kept us intrigued,
but guess what she was doing all the time?
Feeding us her philosophy. Feeding us her
philosophy. Now whether you agreed with her
philosophy or not, you had to admit she was really
good at getting it out there.
Weaving it through the story.
In the dialogue and in the speeches
and in the text. Fabulous.
Novels. Novels are good.
Now here's a little personal advice. Skip the trash.
I mean, you don't...
Sometimes you can find something valuable in a trashy novel.
I wouldn't go through it to find it.
You can find a crust
of bread in a garbage can,
but I wouldn't go through it.
Number one, you don't need
the reputation.
So,
not enough time to read the brilliant stuff,
the good stuff.
Skip the trash, really.
My personal advice on personal development.
Becoming more valuable than you are.
Key.
Next is biographies
and autobiographies. The story of
stories of successful people,
unsuccessful people.
There's some dramatic stuff.
Right?
Over the last hundred years it's been written.
Biographies and autobiographies.
Here's one of the best. The Bible.
The Bible is a unique book
because it's got a list of human stories
on one side of the
ledger, another list of human stories
on the other side of the ledger.
One's called examples and the other's called warnings.
And here's what we've got to have
on biographies and autobiographies.
Both warnings and examples.
In the Bible, the examples.
The Bible says, look at these people's lives.
Follow them. Follow their philosophy.
Follow their advice.
Then we've got the warnings. Right?
Biographies people did. They messed up their life
and threw their life away.
Vaguely important. Both sides of the scenario.
Now if your life story ever
gets in one of those books,
make sure they use it
as an example, not a warning.
Also we need balance.
Both sides. Balance. Good and evil.
Biographies, autobiographies.
You need a book on Gandhi?
You need a book on Hitler?
One to illustrate
how high a human being can go
and the other one to illustrate
what?
How low and despicable
a human being can become.
We need both sides of the scenario.
Next. Accounting.
Got to have a little, at least primary
view of accounting.
Kids have got to start learning
the difference between a debit and a credit.
Next is law. We all need, right,
a little bit. You don't have to be a lawyer
but you got to know contracts.
What to sign, what not to sign.
Backups. Good advice.
How to be safe rather than sorry.
All of us need
a little law. Not a lawyer
but a little law.
Especially these complicated ones.
These complicated days.
Everything's in court these days.
I learned this the hard way.
Company wanted to borrow money.
Long time ago.
Up in Canada.
Company wanted to borrow some money.
The bank said, well, yes,
we will loan the company the money
if Mr. Rohn will sign
personally.
And I wanted
to play hero and I
knew the company could pay it.
Quarter of a million dollars.
So I signed.
No problem.
Sure enough, within less than a
year they paid it all back.
Quarter of a million dollars.
I am now a hero.
Well,
about a year later
this company gets in financial trouble.
They go back to the bank
and borrow this quarter of a million dollars
again.
I said,
I hope my phone doesn't ring because
I won't sign the note this time.
I knew they were in trouble.
I knew they were probably going to go bankrupt.
My phone never rang.
I'm off the hook.
Sure enough, within less than a year
the company goes bankrupt. Can't pay.
But I get this letter from the bank saying,
Dear Mr. Rohn,
Since the company cannot perform its obligation
and pay this quarter of a million dollars,
and since we have here your personal guarantee,
would you please send us your check
for a quarter of a million dollars?
I said, hey, hold it, hold it.
There must be some mistake here.
I signed that first note
and they paid it all back.
I wouldn't have signed the second note.
I didn't sign the second note.
Well,
what I didn't know I had originally signed
was a continuing guarantee.
So, now I know
what the word continuing means.
I'm asking you to study a little law,
know what to sign,
know how to defend yourself,
say, hey, we'll get back,
don't sign too quickly.
I mean, there's all kinds of things here.
Be a student.
Don't be lazy in learning.
How to defend as well as nourish.
How to grow as well
as take care of your enemies.
You've got to learn.
Let your library indicate that you're a serious student
about personal relationships with your family,
gifts and skills,
economics,
and all the rest.
Here's the next one.
Economics.
We're going to study that when
we come back from our break.
Economics. We're going to cover,
especially for the kids today,
how to become financially independent.
We're going to let the adults listen.
I've been teaching kids for the last 18, 19 years
how to be rich by 40,
35 if you're extra bright.
Most kids think they're extra bright, they go for 35.
Or much sooner
they find a unique opportunity.
We're going to get into that.
Be a student of economics.
Next, culture, sophistication.
Don't leave that out of your life.
Culture, sophistication.
Culture is part of the fabric of the nation.
Culture is what makes us different
than dogs and animals.
Culture is what makes us
different from the barbarians.
Culture,
sophistication.
Be a student of the dance
and the art and the music,
and all the rest of it.
All the rest of those extraordinary
human values that are possible for us
all to participate in, as well as to enjoy.
Be a student of culture.
And the last one is spirituality.
Study it from the Bible
and all the related books about spirituality.
If you're a believer, study and practice.
Let your library show
you're a serious student.
Next, keep a journal.
Shelf said,
Mr. Owen, not only be a student,
but the good ideas
that you develop from the books.
Keep a separate journal.
Write all this stuff down.
Here's what he said.
Don't trust your memory.
If you're serious about becoming
wealthy and powerful and sophisticated
and healthy, influential,
cultured, unique,
keep a journal.
Don't trust your memory.
If you listen to something valuable,
write it down.
If you come across something important,
Now, I used to take notes on pieces of paper
and torn off corners and backs of old envelopes
and restaurant placemats
and long sheets and narrow sheets
and little sheets and pieces
thrown in a drawer.
Found out, best way, keep a journal.
I've been keeping these journals now
since age 25.
It makes up a valuable part of my own learning
and it's a valuable part of my life.
I've been keeping them in my library.
My own journals now form a good portion
of my own library.
The stuff.
I'm trying to get kids to do like I do.
Be a buyer of empty books.
Kids find it interesting I buy an empty book.
Especially at my status in life.
What did I pay for this one?
Kids say, $26 for an empty book?
Why would you do that?
Well, the reason I paid $26 is
to press me.
To see if I can't find something worth $26
to put in here.
And I'm telling you, all my journals are private.
But if you got a
hold of one of my journals
you wouldn't have to look very far
until you would say,
this is worth more than $26.
I must admit,
if you got a glimpse of Mr. Rohn's journals
you'd have to say he is a
serious student.
Not just committed to his craft
but committed to life,
committed to skills,
committed to learning.
To see what I can do with seed and soil
and sunshine and rain and miracle
and possibilities and turn it into equities
of life and treasure, family relationships,
enterprise,
sales, management, gifts galore.
Everything you want!
All available, especially in America.
I'm asking you, keep a journal.
I call it one of
the three treasures to leave behind.
Let me give you that.
One of the three treasures to leave behind.
Number one is your pictures.
Take a lot of pictures.
Did you ever look back?
Right?
Two or three generations,
just a handful of photographs way back there.
Wouldn't it be something if there was
album after album,
thousands of pictures to help tell the story?
A picture's worth
a thousand words.
Don't be lazy in capturing the event.
How long does it take to capture the event?
A fraction of a second.
How long does it take to miss the event?
Errors in judgment
or disciplines take lots of pictures.
Help tell the story.
Click, click, got it.
Key.
I go to Taiwan to lecture.
Taipei, Taiwan.
Grand Hotel,
a neat place to do a weekend seminar.
I got a thousand students.
Guess how many cameras?
One thousand cameras!
They all bring their cameras.
They wouldn't miss the event.
Take pictures.
Takes me more time to take pictures
than it does to do the lectures.
Here's my new American friend.
Click, click, save it.
Got it. A thousand words, each one.
What a scenario.
Don't miss the pictures.
When you're gone, one of the things to leave behind,
the treasure in picture
as well as in words.
Key.
Your library.
The library that you gathered,
that taught you,
that instructed you,
that helped you to defend your ideals,
that helped you to develop a philosophy,
that helped you to become wealthy and powerful
and healthy and sophisticated and unique.
The library that helped you conquer some disease.
The library that helped you to conquer poverty.
The library that caused you
to walk away from the ghetto.
The library,
the books that instructed you,
fed your mind
and fed your mind.
Your soul.
Leave your library behind.
One of the greatest gifts you can leave behind
is your library.
Stepping stones out of the darkness into the light.
Your library.
So leave your books behind.
Your books will be more valuable than your couch.
Your books, your books,
your books.
And third is your journals.
The ideas that you picked up.
The notes you took at seminars like this.
Wherever you found an occasion
to gather something valuable
and put it in here so
you could go back over it.
Go back over it.
Repetition is the mother of skill.
Read it one more time. Learn it one more time.
See if you can digest it one more time.
Let it coach you one more time.
Let it teach you one more time.
Let it inspire you one more time.
Words are inspirational.
The lyrics of a song.
And not just read it once.
That's why we put our stuff on cassettes
so you can go through
it again and again and again.
If you hear a beautiful song
that does something to you, you don't say,
well that's enough. Don't need to hear that again.
No. Wouldn't you want to hear it again?
Hear it again. Hear it again.
Let it instruct you. Let it feed you.
Let it teach you.
Take you on wings of emotional journeys.
Wouldn't you want to do that again?
The answer is yes. That's what's so important.
And here's what's important.
One of the things to leave behind. That's your journals.
All the stuff you took the meticulous time to gather.
One of the greatest proofs that you were
a serious student.
Taking pictures, that's pretty easy.
Buying a book at a bookstore,
that's pretty easy.
Here's one that's a little more challenging.
Be student enough of your own life
and your own future and your own destiny.
Be student enough to take the time
to keep the notes and keep the journal.
You'll be so glad you did.
What a treasure to leave behind
when you go.
Your journals.
I wouldn't be without mine now.
I'm in Carmel, California.
One of my favorite places.
It's where I wrote my
first book called Seasons of Life.
I went to this little church one Sunday morning.
First time I'd been there.
Little small church. I don't know, 150 people.
Classic sermon that morning.
Classic sermon.
One of the best I've ever
heard in all of my life.
I happened to be there.
And I had my journal.
While this sermon is going on
I can't believe it was so powerful.
It was so precise. It was so unique.
It was so powerful.
And I've got my journal and I'm taking notes.
Taking notes of this classic sermon.
Guess how many other people were taking notes?
Approximately, guess.
How many do you suppose?
It looked like, best as I could tell,
I'm the only one
taking notes of this
classic sermon.
Now since I'm a stranger there
and it's the first time I've been there,
I'm taking these notes.
People started looking, who is he?
What's he doing?
I started feeling just a little bit uncomfortable.
I'm still writing.
Now I'm feeling kind of like a spy.
I could hear some of them say, he's going
to get out of here with some of this stuff.
And I did. I did.
I'm the guy that walked away
with the stop.
I'm asking you to be no less
sincere and be no less
committed to the advancement of your
philosophy, the set of the sail.
Talk about have your best year ever
this year and then get ready for
next year, your very best year ever
and they'll start being the best, the best,
the best year after year. If you'll commit yourself
to some of this simple stuff called personal
development, start with a walk around the block.
Start with a refinement of your philosophy.
Start with the teaching of your own fabulous
mind where all the answers are.
I can only give you a few answers
from my own experience. The rest of all
the magical answers are within the
confines of your own mind, but it takes the book
takes the cassettes, takes the videos
personal conversation, sermons
lyrics from songs,
dialogue from the movie.
Let your heart be stirred by words.
Find ways to capture
part of your personal development quest.
Now here's
the last subject on personal development just before
we take our break.
Isn't this good stuff?
I'm telling you this stuff changed my life.
Turned me every way but loose.
I've never been the same since
a teacher gave me some of this simple instruction.
How to go from where you
are to where you want to go.
How to go from what you
are to what you want to become.
How to go from pennies to treasure.
How to go from nothing to fortune.
It's all within the confines of this stuff
that I've been trying to share with you.
Laboring best I can.
Words are clumsy at doing your try.
But I'm doing my best today.
And I'm excited about it.
I appreciate you taking all these good notes.
I'm good students today.
I appreciate that.
Do you think you're doing well?
I'm sure I'll be.
Develop these five abilities
as part of your personal development quest.
I call them The Five Abilities.
Here's the first one.
Develop the ability to absorb.
The ability to soak it up like you're doing today.
Be like a sponge.
Don't miss anything.
And not just the words,
it's true, don't miss the words
But don't miss the atmosphere, don't
miss the color, don't miss the scenario
Don't miss what's going on
Most people are just trying to get through the day
Here's what I want you to be committed to do
Learn to get from the day
Don't just get through it, get from it
Learn from it, let the day teach you
Join the university of life
What a difference that'll make in your future
Commit yourself to learning, commit yourself to absorbing
Be like a sponge, get it, don't miss it
I've got a personal friend of
mine who's so gifted in this area
I think he has soaked up and
remembers everything that's ever happened to him
He can tell you as a teenager where he
was and what he did and what he said
And what she said and how they
felt and the color of the sky
And what he said and what she said
And what she said and how they
felt and the color of the sky
And what was going on that day
And the reason is because he gets
it, he gets it, he gets it
I'm telling you it's more exciting
to have him go to Acapulco
Come back and tell you about
it than it is to go yourself
He's unbelievable
He's got this extraordinary gift
And why is it?
When he's there he doesn't miss anything
Here's a good phrase for you to jot down
Wherever you are, be there
Be there to absorb it all
Be there to soak it up
Take a picture if you can
But take pictures of your mind
Let your soul and heart take pictures
Get it, capture it, absorb it
It's such an important ability to develop
The ability to get it, don't miss it
Don't be casual in getting it
Key phrase, casualness leads to casualties
Second
Learn to respond
The ability to respond means let life touch you
Don't let it kill you but let it touch you
Let sad things make you sad
Let happy things make you happy
I'm telling you give in to the emotion
Let the emotion strike you
Not just the words, not just the image
Let the feelings strike you
Let the emotions strike you
Here's what's important
Our emotions need to be as educated as our intellect
Our emotions need to be
educated as well as our intellect
It's important to know how to feel
It's important to know how to respond
It's important to let life in
Let it touch you
I'm the greatest guy in the
world to take to the movies
I get into a good movie
I want to be in a good movie
I want a good movie
Make me laugh, make me cry
Scare me to death
Teach me something
Take me high, take me low
Just don't leave me
As I was when I came in
Touch me, do something to me
Wow
I picked up the newspaper in Australia
The advertisement says, see Dr. Zhivago on the big screen
I said, my gosh
I gotta go see it on the big screen
I'd seen it, you know, two or three times before
But the big screen
I love the old theaters, right?
The balconies and the chandeliers and
the draperies and all this stuff
The big screen
So I go one more time, see Dr. Zhivago
And sure enough, I'm swept away one more time
Story of the Russian Revolution, Dr. Zhivago
And that whole scenario
I had always missed the importance of
the ending of that movie until this time
The other times I missed it
I'm telling you, this time
I got it
Comrade General said, Tanya, how
did you come to be lost?
After he found her, right?
Said, how did you come to be lost?
And she said, well, I was just lost
He said, no, how did you come to be lost?
She said, well, we were, you know, the city
was on fire when we were running to escape
And I was lost
He said, no, how did you come to be lost?
And that's what she didn't want to say
He finally pressed the button and
said, no, I was just lost
He asked her again, how
did you come to be lost?
And she said, well, while we were running
through the city and it was on fire
My father let go of
my hand and I was lost
That's what she didn't want to say
Comrade General said, Tanya, that's what
I've been trying to tell you
Komarovsky was not your real father
He was not
I'm telling you, I've been looking all over
for you and I think I found you
This man, my relative, Dr. Zhivago, the poet
I'm telling you, he was your father
And Comrade General said, Tanya, I promise you this
If this man, your real father, had been there
I promise you, he would never
have let go of your hand
And I got it
This time I got it
The other times I'm eating popcorn
waiting for the movie to finish
I mean, this time I got it
I got it
I'm asking you to get it
Absorb
Maybe you heard the story
about the evangelist here in Texas
Way back in the horse and buggy days
Used to put up his tent in
You know, these various Texas towns
And hold tent revivals
And he put up his tent
One of these towns
Expected a big crowd to come and hear him preach
And he got there the
first night of the tent revival
And he walked inside the tent
It was empty
And he thought
Something must have happened
must be wrong. He waited till eight o'clock. Nobody
showed up. He waited till 815. Not a soul.
Finally, 830. One lone cowboy wandered up on
his horse, tied his horse up outside, came in,
sat down on the front bench, big empty tent.
So the preacher thought, well, at least I better go
down and talk to the cowboy. So he goes
down and talks to the cowboy and he says, cowboy,
I don't know what to tell you. He said,
I'm the preacher. And this tent was supposed to be
full of people. And he said, something's gone
wrong. I really don't know what to do. I'm
embarrassed. And he said, I don't know what to
do. And the cowboy said, well, you know, I'm
not a preacher. I'm just a cowboy. So I can't
tell you what to do. But he said, I know this.
If I went out to feed my cattle and
only one showed up, I'd at least feed it.
So,
the preacher said, hey, the cowboy is
right. If you've got a message to share,
if there's one person or a thousand, don't
let your ego get in the way. You know,
you should do the best you can. So he
got kind of inspired by this conversation with the cowboy,
jumped up on the platform, started preaching
as if the tent was full of people.
And he was so inspired. He just
kept going, kept going, went for an hour,
went for an hour and
15 minutes, hour and a half.
Finally, wound down and quit. Come down off the
platform, talked to the cowboy again, said, well, cowboy,
what did you think of my sermon? Cowboy said, well, I'm
not a preacher, so I can't really tell. I'm just a cowboy.
But he said, I know this. If I went out to feed my cattle and
only one showed up, I'd feed it, but I wouldn't dump the whole load on it.
So,
if it seems like,
that's good.
That's good.
Well,
that's good.
That's good.
I think we're dumping the whole load here today.
I guess we really are.
But you guys are working hard.
Does anybody have four pages of notes?
Oh,
Oh, wonderful.
Wonderful.
Oh, wonderful. My job.
I'm getting it done.
Wonderful.
We should give a prize one
of these days for the most notes.
Fantastic.
I congratulate you.
You're working as hard as I am.
I appreciate that.
Everybody's okay? Say I'm okay. All right. I'd love
to take you with me as my traveling audience.
Wow. We've covered the first two
abilities in the personal development quest.
One is the ability to absorb. Don't miss
anything. Pay attention. Good watchword for the 90s.
Pay attention. Things are moving so fast these
days. You got to pay attention. Pick it up.
Soak up the colors. Soak up the sounds. Soak
up what's going on. Second, respond. Let life touch you.
Let the emotions affect you as well as the sights.
Now here's the third ability. Develop the ability to reflect.
Reflect means go back over. Study it again.
Go back over these notes that you're taking today.
Go back through the cassettes one more time.
Read the text one more time. But there's more
to it than that. Go back over your day.
I call it run the tapes again so that the
day locks in firmly. Here's some good times to reflect.
One, at the end of the day. Take a few minutes
at the end of the day. Go back over the day.
Who'd you see and what'd they say and
what happened? How'd you feel? What went on?
So that you capture that day. A day
is a piece of the mosaic of your life.
Number one.
Number one, don't treat it casual. Number two, get from the day. And then number three, go back over the day
so that it locks in that experience, the knowledge, the sights, the sounds, the panorama, the color, emotion, picture of the day.
Just lock it in so that it will serve
you for the future. Having that day, not missing.
Next, take a few hours at the
end of the week. Call time to reflect.
Go back over your day timer. Go back
over your calendar. Go back over your appointment book.
Where did you go and who did you see
and how did it feel and what went on?
Capture that week. A week is
a pretty good chunk of time.
Next, take half a day at the
end of the month. Call time to reflect.
And do the same thing again. Go back over what you read.
Go back over what you heard. Go back over what you saw.
Go back over what you saw.
Go back over the feelings to
capture it so that it serves you.
Next, take a weekend at the end of the year.
To establish this year now firmly in your consciousness.
Firmly in your experience bank.
So that you've got it so that it never disappears.
Good ability to acquire. The ability to reflect.
The ability to remember.
So that you can remember again what you have lost.
Even if it's just a little bit.
Just remember, remember, remember.
It's so valuable to be able to remember.
The thought, remember the idea, remember the
experience, remember the occasion, remember the day.
Remember the weather, remember the emotion, remember
the complexity, remember the highs, remember the lows.
So valuable at the end of the day.
Lock that day in.
Lock the month in. Lock the
week in. Lock the year in.
in. Old Testament says a unique scenario
unfolded according to the law and that
was they worked nine years and the
tenth year was a sabbatical. The tenth year
work nine take the tenth year and not
just to relax not just to replenish not
maybe just to get physically in shape change
of pace we call it in the modern
society but not just for that I'm
sure that in ancient days that sabbatical was
to go over the last nine years what
went right and what went wrong and what
worked well and what didn't work well and
how did you grow and how did you
learn and how did you change and what
have you got now after nine years that
you didn't have at the beginning of
the nine years see that's so valuable a
sabbatical.
A sabbatical.
Some time, some time. There's also
something to be said for solitude when
you reflect sometimes you can reflect
with somebody husband and wife reflect
on the past year right parents reflect
with their children on the past year how
did we do it and how didn't we
do it and how could we improve colleagues can
reflect with each other but now here's
one of the most important you've got to
learn to reflect with yourself
there's something to be said for
solitude there's something to be said
for taking those occasions to shut out
the world and shut out everything else for
a while for a while I've got a motor
home that's how I do my motorcycle on
the back and I head for the mountains
and ride the Jeep trails where there's
very few human beings on the Jeep
trails or out in the desert somewhere it's
called my time to get away and I'm
going to get out of here.
When you live a very public life you treasure solitude.
A chance to reflect go back over my life
go back over my skills go back over my
experiences alone alone there are some things
you need to do alone ponder think
wonder read study absorb soak in see
if you can't become better this year than
you were last year better the next
nine than you were the first nine solitude.
There's even a more modern advice that
says go to the closet for time of
meditation time of prayer go to
the closet closet meaning what away and
there's even a graphic description of the
away said enter into your closet and
what got some students here I'm sure what close
the door for what just to shut out the world.
Close the door.
For what?
Just to shut out the world.
Just to shut out everything.
Life is experience experience experience and
touching and seeing and looking and doing
and acting and disciplines and all the
stuff but sometimes this is where this reflecting
is so important to shut the door just
shut the door and wonder prayer contemplation thinking
and let things move in to your consciousness
and awareness that no other way can it be
done right flying down the freeway.
I'm telling you.
I'm telling you it's difficult to get through
so many things to do it's difficult to get
through the times of solitude times to reflect
so this is so valuable learn to reflect now
here's why it's important to reflect to make
the past more valuable to serve you for the
future.
Here's what's really powerful learning to gather
up the past and invested in the future
gather up today and invested in tomorrow gather
up this week and invested in the next week
gather up.
This is what you're going to do
next year and invested in the next year.
See that's so powerful rather than just hanging
on one more year hanging in there seeing what's
going to happen learn study.
This is part of the personal development
quest becoming better than you are more valuable
than you are not just in terms of
economics in terms of motherhood in terms of fatherhood
in terms of being a better brother
better colleague making a better contribution to
the family to society to the community to
the church to the office to the commitment
to the partnership.
Doesn't matter what it is that has value
work on yourself then you bring more value
to the partnership to the marriage to
the franchise to the corporation to the enterprise
to the community to the nation
self development personal development the best contribution
you can make to someone
else's self development not self sacrifice.
Self sacrifice only earns
contempt self development earns respect.
Pity the mother who says I'm just going
to give up my life for my children.
Self sacrifice is not noble.
Self investment is noble from self development.
If I work on myself and become more
valuable think of what that'll do for our friendship.
I used to use the old expression you take
care of me and I'll take care of you.
I found out how shallow and short ended that
was and I changed it to read like this I'll
take care of me for you.
If you will please take care of you for me.
And this is part of it.
The personal development quest.
The personal development that we work harder
on ourselves than we do on our job.
Now we bring that to the friendship.
Now we bring that to the marriage.
Now we bring that to the family relationship as
a father as a mother and we develop the
strength and we develop the power.
That's key.
And it takes I think this scenario of
disciplines these abilities to acquire those gifts and
those skills that value so that we bring more.
Now we bring more to the next week.
We bring more to the next month.
We bring more to the next year.
If you follow this absorb respond and reflect.
I said to my father when he
was about to turn 76 his 76th birthday.
I said dear father of mine.
Can you imagine what it's going to be like
to gather up the last 75 years of your life
and invest them in your 76th year.
What a difference of philosophy rather
than just hanging on one more year.
Gather up 75 and invest them in the next one.
Gather up the last six years
and invested in the next year.
See that's so powerful in communication
which we're going to study soon.
So powerful.
So consider this one the ability to absorb
second the ability to respond third the ability
to reflect.
Here's number four develop the ability to act take action.
Not hasty if it isn't required.
But don't.
Don't lose much time.
Here's the time to act.
When the idea is hot and the emotion is strong.
That's the time to act.
You say Mr. Rohn I'd like
to have a library like yours.
See if you feel strong about that what you've got
to do is get the first book and then get
the second book before the feeling
passes and before the idea gets dim.
Action pronto.
Action immediate.
Action as soon as possible.
Because if you don't here's what happens.
We call it the law of diminishing intent.
We intend to when the idea strikes us
we intend to when the emotion is high.
But now if you don't translate that into
action fairly soon now the intent starts to diminish
diminish diminish and a month from now
it's cold year from now can't be found.
So act set up a discipline when the emotions
are high and the idea is strong and clear
and powerful.
That's the time to set up the discipline.
Somebody talks about good health and you're stirred right.
I need to get a book on nutrition.
Get the book before the idea passes and
before the emotion gets cold go for the book.
Start the library.
Start the process.
Fall on the floor.
Do some pushups.
Action.
Gotta take action.
Otherwise the wisdom is wasted.
Otherwise the emotion soon passes unless
you put it into a disciplined activity.
Capture it.
Disciplines is called.
How to capture the emotion and how to
capture the wisdom and translate it into equity disciplines.
Now here's what's important about disciplines.
All disciplines affect each other.
In fact here's a good philosophical phrase.
Everything affects everything else.
Nothing stands alone.
Don't be naive in saying well this doesn't matter.
I'm telling you everything matters.
There are some things that matter.
There are some things that don't matter.
There are some things that matter more
than others but there isn't anything that doesn't
matter.
We all pity the man who says well
this is the only place I let down.
Not true.
Key to take home.
Every letdown affects the rest of your performance.
Every letdown affects the rest.
This is part of the
educational process on personal development.
Okay.
And if you don't take the walk around the
block you probably won't do the apple a day.
If you don't do the apple a day
you probably won't consist you know start building your
library.
If you don't build your library you probably
won't keep a journal and you won't take pictures
and you won't do this.
You won't do wise things with your money.
Won't do wise things with your time.
Won't do wise things with your possibilities
and relationships and the first thing you
know six years of that accumulated
and we say you have messed up.
So the whole key to reversing that process
now is to start picking up these disciplines.
Now here's the positive side.
Every new discipline affects the rest of your disciplines.
Every new one affects the rest.
That's why action is so important.
The least action.
The smallest action.
Take it because when you start accomplishing and
the value starts to return from that one
accident will inspire you to do the next
one and the next one and the next one.
You start walking around the block.
It'll inspire you to get an apple.
Get an apple.
It'll inspire you to get a book.
Get a book.
It'll inspire you to get a journal.
Get a journal.
It'll inspire you to grow.
Develop some skills.
All disciplines affect each other.
Every lack affects the rest.
Every new affects the rest.
The key is to diminish the lack and set
up the new and you've started a whole new life
process.
Key.
Also one more thought on discipline.
Here's the greatest value of discipline.
Self worth.
Self esteem.
People are teaching self esteem these days,
but they don't connect it to disciplines.
They don't connect it to discipline.
The least lack of discipline, and
it starts to erode our psyche.
One of the greatest temptations is to
just ease up a little bit, right?
The slightest lack of doing your
best starts to erode the psyche.
Instead of doing your best, doing
just a little less than your best.
Sure enough, you say, well, it's
just going to affect my sales.
No.
It's going to affect your consciousness.
What?
It's going to affect your philosophy.
Now you've begun in the slightest
way to affect your own philosophy.
Here's the problem with the least neglect.
Neglect starts as an infection.
And if you don't take care
of it, it becomes a disease.
And one neglect leads to another.
And the worst of all, when neglect starts,
it diminishes our self-worth, our self-confidence, our self-value.
You say, well, how can I get back my self-respect?
I'm telling you, you don't
have to go to 29 classes.
All you have to do is start the
smallest discipline that now corresponds to your own philosophy.
Like I should, and I could, and I will.
No longer will I let neglect stack up on me so
that I will have the sorry scenario six years from now,
giving some excuse instead of celebrating my progress.
That's the key to discipline.
Okay?
Let's get kids involved in the least of disciplines.
One more, and then one more, and then another
one, and then another one, and then some more.
And the first thing you know, you're starting
to weave the tapestry of a disciplined life
into which you can pour more wisdom and more
attitude and more strong feeling, more faith and more courage.
Now you've got something, a
vessel in which to put it.
And now the equities start to flow.
And the early return, I'm telling
you, if you'll start this process,
the early return will have you so excited, you'll commit
yourself to this strategy for the rest of your life.
You'll never go back to the old ways.
Join a new crowd.
Join a new group.
The discipline's to do it.
Take action.
I recommended the last time I was
here, the little book, Richest Man in Babylon.
And I said, I've lectured now to over
3 million people in the last 33 years.
And I've recommended this little book
to almost all of them, I think.
Guess how many have actually
gone and got this little book?
Answer, very few.
My best guess is 10%.
Such an easy thing to do.
In that last seminar, right, I suggested this
little book, number one, is easy to find.
Number two, it's easy to buy.
The most you can pay
for it, six, seven, eight dollars.
You can borrow that from your kids.
And number three, it's easy to read.
It's in story form.
That's why I use it for teenagers, teaching them how
to be rich by 40, 35, if you're extra bright.
Much sooner, if you find a unique opportunity.
But if it's easy to find and easy to buy,
and if it's easy to read,
why wouldn't everybody go get it?
We don't know.
What do you know?
You don't know.
I don't know.
Nobody knows.
Here's how profound it is.
Some do and some don't.
Now here's the numbers.
About 10% do.
90% don't or won't.
And we don't know the mystery of that.
And I'm telling you, 10 years from now,
those numbers will still be the same.
10% will, 90% won't.
The numbers don't change.
Only the faces change.
You're looking at one of the faces.
I used to belong to the 90% who
couldn't be bothered even if it was easy.
Guess how many people have a library card?
Wisdom of the world available.
Transform your life in any value amount you want.
By the way, how much
is a library card in Texas?
Free.
Here's what free is.
Easy.
I mean, it can't be any easier than free.
Somebody says, well, would you bring it by?
Well, no.
At least you got to go get it.
No.
Wisdom of the world available.
Transform your life
spiritually, socially, personally, economically,
and every other way.
Teach you how to be rich
and powerful and sophisticated and healthy, influential.
How many people have a library card?
Answer, 3%.
95, 97% couldn't be bothered.
Guy specializes in happy hour,
but he doesn't have a card.
And now readily and quickly blames
the government and blames his company
and blames policy and blames the pay scale.
When if he only knew if he joined
the 3%, here's my advice to you today.
Walk away from the 97%.
Don't talk like they talk.
Don't act like they act.
Don't go where they go.
Don't specialize in what they specialize in.
Throw away the blame list they cling to.
Start you a new life.
You say, well, is it as simple as
getting a library card and join the 3%?
And the answer is, of course.
Of course.
That's how easy this stuff is.
This is so easy.
It's so simple.
It's not complex.
You don't need a 2,000-year-old guru.
You don't need multi-track affirmations.
I'm telling you, don't.
Affirmation without discipline is the beginning of delusion.
T.
Don't let somebody sweep you into
some contrary way to nature itself, says,
unless you labor the miracle of the seed
and the soil and the seasons and God
and all the other stuff that's available, sunshine and rain,
that's not available to you by affirmation.
It is only available to you by labor.
So labor well.
Okay.
Learn well.
Discipline yourself well.
And you can have all the treasures you want.
This stuff's easy and simple.
It's not ocean waves and seagulls.
You don't have to move to Sedona where
all the force fields come together in Arizona.
Let's teach our kids the simple
ways to transform their health, number one.
Their economics, number two.
Their ability to communicate, number three.
Their life and treasure and lifestyle, number four.
Spirituality, number five.
And the list goes on and on.
Let's not leave out any of the least of disabilities.
In the world, we have three major disciplines
that encourage us to do the next one,
to do the next one, to do the next one.
First thing you know, this whole
scenario for you is spinning up
instead of out of control on the negative side.
This is all you got to do.
It's as simple as this.
It's as simple as the
start, committing yourself to life change.
And once you start down this road, I
promise you, you'll join the 10% and the 3%.
We're going to talk financial
independence in just a little while.
Guess how many people can retire from
the income of their own personal resources
when it comes time to retire?
In the most independent country in the
world 95% are dependent 5% are independent
Take charge of your own retirement
I'm telling you if you take charge of your own
retirement through personal development and all these skills we've taught today
Plus what's coming up financial independence? I'm
telling you take charge of your own retirement
You can multiply it at least by five maybe
by 10, maybe by 20, maybe by a hundred
Let the government take care of it some company
take care of it. You got to divide by five
Take charge of your own life take charge of
your own day take charge of your own conversation
Take charge of your own family
take charge of your own possibilities
And learn these skills develop this kind of strategy and I'm telling
you life will open up for you join the 3% join the 10%
Join the 5% walk away from the 95%
In our leadership weekend we teach find out
what poor people read and don't read it
I'm telling you don't talk like they talk lend
a helping hand, but don't fall into the their poor
Philosophical scenario don't blame what they blame
Don't use the excuses they use
it's called the language of the poor
switch gears switch language switch ideas switch
Start with the simplest of disciplines and don't be mean any of
these disciplines the smallest of discipline starts the process of life change
And if you'll invest in this thing called discipline, you can
have whatever you wish. It's called the beginning of a miracle
Now here's the last clue on discipline
do the best you can we covered earlier
But here's a good scenario for
the do the best you can
I've got a good question for you is the best you
can do all you can do and the answer is no
Strangely enough
If we all fell on the floor right now
and did as many push-ups as we possibly could
And let's say for some reason you haven't been
into push-ups lately I can't imagine why but let's say
And let's say the best
you can do is five and
You look up at the rest of us and say hey five
is the best I can do we can tell the look on
Your face, that's probably true. Five
is the best you can do
Now is five all you can do
And
five more
The answer is no, if you rest
a little you can do five more
Wow, and if you rest a
little you can do five more
And if you rest a
little you can do 15 more
How did you get from 5 to 20? It's
a miracle. Did you know you can keep doing
that? Do a little more, rest a little,
do a little more, rest a little and finally
get up to 50 push-ups? Is it possible to
get up to 50 push-ups? Of course! How do
you go from 5 to 50? It's a miracle!
How do you get a miracle going? Number one, do
what you can. Don't leave out what you
can from riding a leather to your mother
in Florida. Start cleaning it all up. Two, doing
the push-ups. Go from 5 to 50. It's a
miracle. Number one, do what you can.
Number two, do the best you can. Here's
number three, rest very little.
Don't rest too long. Why? The weeds
take the garden. Kids have got that figured
out. You can't rest too long. Here's
the clue, make rest a necessity not an
objective.
you can't rest too long. Here's the
clue, make rest a necessity not an objective.
The objective of life is not to rest.
The objective of life is to act. Think of
more disciplines, think of more ways and
means in which to use your own wisdom
and your own philosophy and use your
own attitude, your own faith, your own
courage, your own commitment, your own
desires, your own excitement. Invest it,
invest it, invest it, invest it in
discipline so that it's not wasted. The
smallest of discipline. Thereby transform your life.
Join the 5%, join the 10%, join
the 3%.
Guess when I went and got
this little book, Richest Man in Babylon? The
same day I heard about it, I went and
got it. Somebody says, well, Mr. Oan,
does that make you different than most other
people? And the answer is yes. Somebody says,
well, why is that? We don't know. We
don't know. What do you know? You don't
know, I don't know, none of us knows. Some
do and some don't. The numbers don't
change, only the faces change. From the
those who get in on a seminar like this listen
to a dynamic sermon read a book listen to some
cassettes take seriously the next conversation of a
friend who wants to level with you and do
something about it and you can walk away from the
97 not live there anymore because if you don't the
next six years of your life will be like the last
six mr shoves said to me mr own six years now
you've been working i'm telling you the next six years
your life is going to be like the last six
unless you take advantage and start making
these personal changes i made the changes totally
revolutionized my life so take a look at the next
five years of your life it's going to be like the
last five unless unless unless unless you change
and if you will change everything will change
join the five percent ten years from now
the numbers are going to be the same
but i'm telling you some faces in this audience
can change and start showing up in the three
percent crowd in the
you
five percent crowd in the ten percent crowd
and thereby dynamically affect your life and your
future develop these strengths now here's the
last ability develop the ability to share
pass along to someone else if you've picked up a
good idea today pass it along don't let it stay
pass it along a book if you take one
of these little books i've suggested home and it affects
you pass along say hey i found a book really
helped me i found a book got me thinking i found
a book changed my health i found a book
got me inspired pass it alone pass it along
pass it along here's what's exciting about sharing if you
share with ten different people they get to hear
it once you get to hear it ten times
so it's probably going to do more
for you than it is for them
but it's called what everybody
wins when somebody shares everybody wins
wow share your ideas share your experiences share your
knowledge you can have just as much pleasure in
I do I said giving this seminar.
This is one of my joys in life
Give a seminar like this make the best investment I
can of words and spirit and heart and soul and time
Energy, I don't have to work this hard
But I gladly work this hard why I want the
return your words touch my life see that's heavyweight stuff
You can't buy it with money
But I'm telling you you can get
the same thing started by recommending a book
somebody will read that book and then they'll read another one and
they'll read another one and they'll come to you someday and say
You got me started that book
you recommended turn my lights on
Turn my mind around got me thinking got me pondering and I've been
on track ever since you can get just as much praise as I
Do if you'll share share
With your children share with your colleagues share
with everybody that comes within your grasp shared
Now here's what sharing does not
only helps you helps the person you
Share with here's what else it does makes you bigger
Than you are
If I had a glass of
water up here and it was full
Question can that glass hold
any more water if it's full
If the glass is full
can it hold any more water
The answer is yes
But for it to hold more you
got to pour out what's already in
That's what I'm asking you to do
If you're full of ideas
If you're full of good things, I'm asking you
to pour it out pour it out pour it out
Why I'm telling you more will
be poured in poured in poured in
Next
When you do pour out you become bigger
It's not like a glass that stays the same
Human beings have the ability to grow
and consciousness and awareness and capacity. It's unlimited
Capacity I found out kids don't lack capacity
In Europe the kids speak what
two three four five six languages
When I grew up my father spoke German never
taught me my mother spoke French never taught me
They were trying to get away from all the old world languages back
then had no concept how valuable languages were gonna be in the future
Just didn't know
So they abandoned the German abandoned the French. I
could have learned all three languages instead of just English
My girls went to high school went
to school in the Beverly Hills they've
Turned that around and then they went to
school in Beverly Hills and they've turned that around
In first grade now in Beverly Hills
school system. They offer three languages besides English
French and German Spanish
Why because kids can learn two
languages just as easy as one
Question how many languages can a child learn? Here's how
many as many as you'll take the time to teach them
They do not lack capacity. They only lack teachers
And I'm telling you the same thing
is with you you don't lack capacity
But here's how you expand your capacity
And that is to share what you've got now
you get bigger share some more now you get bigger
I'm here for a very self-interest reason if I share with you my
consciousness grows if I share with you I get to hear this again
Somebody asked me not long ago said mr. On how are you
doing with all this stuff you get on everybody's case pretty hard
How are you doing with all
this stuff you teach I said well
Best I can share with you is this listen
to me very carefully, but don't watch me too closely
I'm not going to be too close
This stuff's easier to lecture on than it is to do
I understand that I'm working on it just like you but hey
Pour out what you've got so that your capacity grows
Now why should you want your capacity to grow very self-interest
reason here it is to hold more of the next experience
You mean to tell me that sitting in this audience some people
will get more out of it than others and the answer is yes
If you haven't been into expanding your own capacity
lately, you might not get much from this seminar
But if you've been into expanding your capacity you've
been sharing and you've been doing all this stuff
I'm telling you no telling what all this could mean to
you today this chance to grow change develop absorb take in
I'm asking you to expand and grow
So you can hold more of the next experience
some people can't be very happy you could pour happiness
Out on the whole world
some people can't be very happy
Why they're not big enough
If you're small you don't get much
Small and comprehension small and the ability
to think and wonder small and appreciation
No matter how much is poured out prosperity
can be poured out on the whole country
Some people don't get much why they're too small too small
and they're thinking too small in their ability to share have not
Expanded to their full capacity
Don't be like that
Now some people aren't gonna get much
because they've got their cup turned upside down
You couldn't put anything in
Learn to share it's a glorious glorious experience
Okay enough on personal development
Let's cover now setting goals. Let me show
you something to turn me every way but loose
I've never been the same
since I found out about it
Learning how to set goals
Not long after I met mr.
Shoaf we're having breakfast one morning
Mr. Shoaf said mr. Oh now that we've gotten acquainted. We know
each other fairly. Well, he said maybe one of the best ways
I can help you
He said let me see your current list of
goals. Let's go over them and talk about it
And I said what I
Don't have a list
He said well, mr. Rohn if you
don't have a list of your goals
He said I can guess your
bank balance within a few hundred dollars
Which he did and
That got my attention. I
Said you mean my bank balance would change if
I had a list of goals. He said drastically
So that day I became a student of setting
goals and I've used it to dynamically affect my life
I've taught it to some of my business colleagues.
We use it to do business around the world
setting goals
It can turn out to be a drama
for
Your life. Here's what goals
are your vision of the future
Your vision of the future now
there's two ways to face the future
one
with apprehension
Number two with anticipation
Guess how most people face the future
With apprehension why major reason?
Why they don't have it well designed
They've left the design of their future to somebody else
And if you don't make plans of your own
guess what you'll probably fall into someone else's plans
Guess what someone else may have planned for you
Not much you got to make
a list of this not much stuff
I'm telling you people all their
lives count on this not much list
If there's only a short list.
We need to know that way
What's your rush on the at-bats?
When you get there?
Listen you've got a lot of things to learn
He's reveal
Well, I'd rather make time right here
It's place
But judging one way or another
That is fair
I think
nehme
time the answer all this is
down this whole scenario list. Most
people all their lives with their
fingers crossed count on this not much
list. That's why ten years from now
they'll be driving what they don't want
to drive, living where they don't want to
live, wearing what they don't want to
wear, doing what they don't want to do,
having what they don't want to have,
maybe become what they didn't want to
become and it all starts by counting
on something that's not gonna count much.
You say well then how can my
life dramatically change? You got to count on
yourself and here's one of the things
you got to count on, your ability to
design the future. It's called the promise
and the promise of the future if
you'll design it well can have an
awesome effect on your life but if you
face the future with apprehension you'll
take hesitant steps all day, uncertain
steps all day and if you take uncertain
steps all day for six years you can
imagine how empty your life can be.
We've got to help our children.
We've got to help our kids with the promise
of the future. Now here's what's connected to the
promise, the price. The price to pay but
I'm telling you the price is easy if the
promise is clear. One of the better notes
to make for today. The price is easy if
the promise is clear and powerful but
the price seems almost too much to pay,
too much to get over, too much
to accomplish if the promise isn't clear. If
the promise isn't powerful. I'm telling
you kids will pay the disciplines if
they can see the promise.
One of our biggest challenges as parents in
the 90s is to help our kids see the
promise of the future. That's why
I'm teaching financial independence, how to
become wealthy and powerful and
sophisticated and healthy, unique, all of
the stuff kids would hope to go for.
It's all possible. This is America. That's the
promise of the future. The price?
A few simple disciplines practiced every day
and I'm telling you the kids will
pay the price of the simple disciplines if
they can see the promise of the future. But if
they can't see the promise of the future, that's the price.
But if they can't see the promise of the
future, that's the price. The price of the future.
If they can't see, they don't want to pay. And the
same is true of all of us. We will pay the most
extraordinary disciplines if we can see
the promise of the future called setting
goals. So I'm asking you to get a handle
on the future. I'm asking you not to leave
it to anyone else. Don't leave it
to the company. Companies got their own
goals. I'm asking you to set your
own goals, your personal goals, income goals
and financial goals and health goals and
spiritual goals. Where do you want to go
and what do you want to do and what do
you want to see and what do you want to do?
And what do you want to see and what do
you want to see and what do you want to see?
That's it. Promise of the future. Design
your own future. It's within your hands
and your capacity to do so. Here's
how simple now goal setting is. It's not
mysterious. You don't have to anchor. You
don't have to focus. You don't have to
visualize. No that's it. Here's how simple
goal setting is. Changed my life. Decide
what you want and write it down. I
mean that's how profound this stuff is. Decide
what you want and write it down. Make a list.
Where do you want to go. What do you want to do.
What do you want to see. What do you want to be.
What do you want to have.
What do you want to share. What projects would like
to support. What would you like to be known for
What skills would you like to learn.
Some extraordinary things you'd like to do. Ordinary
things you'd like to do. Silly little things you'd
like to do. Very important things you'd like to
do. Decide. Decide on all that stuff and
write it down. Write it down. Write it down.
That's how simple this stuff is. And it's your own
private list. if it's really private. You know on your
Put some stuff in code where nobody can
understand it if this list fell into unfriendly hands
And simple things whatever
Foolish things doesn't matter cheer list. I
had a little revenge on my first list
Budget finance who used to harass me. I
Got two or three payments behind this one guy
called incessantly said we're gonna come get your car drag
It rear end up down the
street in front of your neighbors
Oh
Put me down something fierce when I
met Shove got my life straightened out
One of the first things on
one of my lists was budget finance
And when I finally got the
money I needed a little drama
in my life
Finally got the money to pay him off. I
put it in small bills in a big briefcase
Walked into the budget finance office on Wilshire
Boulevard in Los Angeles the guy who harassed
me so often his desk was about three back
I opened the door walked in right up to his
desk stood right in front of him. Never said a word
He said well, what are you doing here?
Didn't say a word. I opened up this briefcase dumped this
pile of money all over his desk. I said count it
It's all there I'll never be back
turned around walked out slammed the door
Now that might not be noble but
You got to try it at least one time
Pay off with a little drama
Got to check them off my list
Keep your list with you. I keep my list in
my journal so that I can go back five years ago
Here was my list and I'm a little
embarrassed. Here's what I thought was so important now
How my philosophy has changed from ten years ago
five years ago three years ago. Here's my old list
Here's my new list. Here's what's valuable to me
now. Here's what I want my life to be now
Here's where I want to go what I
want to do what I want to see
Keep your lists of goals so that it shows your growth
shows your ability to change and grow your philosophy grows and expands
What's valuable?
Setting goals. It doesn't matter how small
foolish it is put it on your list
my Japanese friend Toro Ikeda
Put on his first list a Caucasian gardener
But that was
Like
Have you got this profound thing now and setting
goals here's how profound it is decide what you want
Write it down get together with your wife decide get
together with your kids decide get together with your business colleagues
Decide write it down make a
list. Okay, that's how easy it is
Now let me give you one more scenario on
setting goals when I started making my first list
Mr. Shope said mr. Own looks like we're gonna be together
for a while. He said I've got a suggestion for you
He said I think one of the first goals you
ought to set your 25 year old American male sure
You've made some mistakes, but now
you're on the road to better things
You got a family worth it
Reasons makes the difference
And he said you've got every reason to do this
He said why don't you among
all the goals you're gonna set?
said why don't you set a
goal to become a millionaire a
Millionaire this is America
All the possibilities are available. Why don't you set a goal
to become a millionaire said it's got a nice ring to it
Millionaire enough zeros to impress your accountant
and
He said here's why now I thought
the man doesn't need to teach me why
I'm thinking wouldn't it be great
to have a millionaires job?
To have a million dollars.
He said no, that's not it
Here's why and I had one of the greatest lessons
I ever learned and I'm about to share it with you
This will be worth the price of being here today if
you can capture what I'm about to share with you babysitter fees
Whatever else you pay some of you missed some sales today
to be here. So this is a costly day for you
But what I'm about to share with you changed my whole life.
Here's what mr. Shove said set a goal to become a millionaire
And he said here's why
for what it will make you?
To achieve it
And I got one of the greatest classes
in one sentence I've ever received in my life
Set a goal that'll make you stretch that far
For what it will make of you to achieve it
What a brand new reason for setting goals
What an all-encompassing challenge to have a better vision of the future
what for to see what it will make of you to achieve it?
And here's why the greatest value in life is not what
you get the greatest value in life is what you become
Major question to ask on the job is not
what am I getting here? That's not the major question
The major question to ask
is what am I becoming here?
It's not what you get that makes you
valuable. That's what you become that makes you valuable
So Shove said set a goal to become a millionaire
For what it will make of you to achieve it
Then he said would you finally have become a millionaire?
Now he said what's important is not the money.
I thought wow. I've got some more to learn
He said no no mr
And I'm telling you, honestly, you could just give the money
away now. I did better than that, right I told you
I lost it all
I'm rich. By the time I'm 31. I'm
a millionaire. I'm broke by the time. I'm 33
So I didn't have to give it all away
I lost it all
Foolish mistakes I made
That I'm a farm boy from Idaho
that early money drove me bonkers. I
Used to say how many colors does
it come in? I'll buy them all I
Just went I went crazy over
that first money. I just went crazy
And then I made that
one foolish mistake right continuing guarantee
I mean, you know, I'm so naive off
the farm. I don't know what continuing means
And a few other mistakes and
by the time I'm 33 I'm broke
Now I've made and lost millions since then
But what an experience that was and I'm telling you the
man was right when I finally was broke at age 33
Guess what? I discovered my money did not mean that
much. It represented only a fraction of all my assets
Shove said once you become a millionaire, mr.
Rohn you can give all the money away
Because he says what's important is not the
money. What's important is the person you've become
Now give me let me give you the key phrase on setting goals
set the kind of goals that will make something of you to achieve
Them set the kind of goals that
will make something of you to achieve them
Always keep that in mind what will this make of
me if I set this goal and go for it?
Not only will I achieve it, but what
will it make of me in the process?
What a whole new concept on setting goals
Now there's two parts to this
and then we're wrapping up goals
Here's the first part now in this goal setting for
what you become number one. Don't set your goals too low
Interesting we teach in leadership
You'll find it on the
cassettes. Don't join an easy crowd
You won't grow
Go where the expectations are high?
Go where the demands are high
Go where the demands are high?
Go where the pressure is on to perform to grow
to change to develop to read to study to develop skills
I belong to a small group. We do business around
the world. You cannot believe the expectations at that level
What we expect of each other in
terms of excellence far beyond average why
So that we can each grow so
that we can receive from the group
We can contribute to the group something
unprecedented. It's called living at the summit
Go where the demands are high go where the
expectations are strong so that it'll provoke you push you
Urgently insist that you not remain the same for the next
couple of years the next five years that you'll grow and change
So don't set your goals too low
The guy says well, I don't need much.
Well, then you don't need to become much
Now here's the last part on
setting goals don't compromise don't sell out
Don't compromise don't sell out
There were some things I went
for back in those early years
That I paid too big a price for if
I'd have known how much it was gonna cost me
I never would have paid but I didn't know
Don't sell out
ancient phrase says count the cost
count the cost count the cost
cost
An ancient story says Judas got the money
you say well, that's a success story. No, no
It's true 30 pieces of silver in those days was a
sizable fortune you say well if a guy's got a fortune, right?
That's a success story. No, you don't understand.
His name was Judas. Doesn't that ring a bell?
Judas you say oh, yes Judas Judas the
traitor. That's right. The traitor got the money
Doesn't that change the story and the
answers? Of course it changes the store
a
Interesting is it Quang internet
track
the money from becoming a traitor
Cash
money bank
is not country
He oben
Wall flop
You're running or you can crash
Where's your money
You can tricks
right
that you can't
Yes, I'm an gamer
So that you take product
to world
an
Eric
that it does have towards itр
the best that ever was in the world and a better
and a better and similar to you is to talk about
come from outside. The greatest source
of unhappiness comes from inside. And here's
where the erosion starts, doing a little
less than you could. That's where the beginning
little infection of unhappiness starts, doing a
little less than you can, not feeling that
good about yourself. So don't let that happen. Judas
is unhappy. He says, what do I do? He
says, oh, just take the money back. Walked
in where he got the money and said, here,
take this money. I'm unhappy. They said, heck
with you, Judas. We got what we wanted.
You got what you wanted out. They threw
him out with his money. Judas says, well, what
do I do now? He says, oh, clever. Should
have thought of this first. I'll just throw the
money away. And he proceeded to throw his
fortune away. Why would he throw his fortune
away? He was so unhappy with himself. And
that's not even the end of the scenario. After
he threw his fortune away, he couldn't change
what he became, a traitor. And now in total
abject frustration, he goes out and hangs himself.
His worthless self, which all traitors should do,
save to stake the money. Why such a tragic
end? Because he was so unhappy with himself. He
sold out. He sold out. He paid too big
a price. Ancient script sums it all up and
said, what if you gained the whole world and
it cost you your soul? Too big a price
to pay. If you got the whole world, you're going
to have to pay for it.
Don't sell out. Don't sell out. Don't
compromise your values. Don't compromise your virtues.
Don't compromise your philosophy. Keep. Here's the
key word. Beware. If Judas could speak
back, he'd probably say beware. Two good
words from ancient script. One, behold the positive
word. Behold the possibilities. Behold the
opportunity. Behold the drama. Behold the
awesomeness. Behold the uniqueness.
Behold the majesty. Behold. Behold. What a
good word. But here's the other word. Beware.
Beware. Beware. Don't sell out. Mark well what
you become in pursuit of what you want.
But I'm inspiring you, hopefully, to set the
kind of goals that will transform your life,
make you far better than you
are, far stronger than you are.
Okay. Isn't this good advice?
Yeah, that's right.
This is such good stuff. I
should have paid to get in, right?
Fabulous.
What should a child do with a dollar?
Let me give you the best advice.
Let me give you the best advice. The best advice
is to get a job. You want to be a good
person?
You want to be successful in life?
Yeah.
That's the advice I've got.
And this is called a sort of middle of
the road scenario. And I'll show you how these
numbers may change, but here's what I teach.
Kids never spend more than 70 cents.
Now you got to pick some number.
When I met Mr. Shelf, I was at about 110%.
But remember this, if your outgo exceeds
your income, your upkeep becomes your downside.
upkeep becomes your downfall. Good little scenario. So
here's the number that I found works best in
developing a good financial plan. Never spend more than
70 cents out of every dollar from now on.
Now kids ask me what?
What do you do with the other 30
cents? Here's my best advice. 10 cents, charity.
Charity. 10% charity. Supporting worthy projects,
helping people who cannot help themselves.
Some churches teach tithe, peace, portion, turning
back part of what you take out.
Excellent, excellent philosophy. That's what that
10% is. And nothing teaches children
responsibility and character better than generosity.
No school, no class, no teacher can teach
character better than the simple act of generosity.
10 cents out of every dollar. Now you can pick
your own number. I'm just giving you my best scenario.
Now the time to start this is when the amounts
are small. Easy to give a dime out of a dollar.
I'm telling you kids will give you 10 cents
out of every dollar if it's part of their philosophy,
if you sell them on it. And that's the time
to start when it's easy. 10 cents out of a dollar.
It's a little harder to
give 100,000 out of a million.
Someone says, oh, if I had a million
dollars, I'd give 100,000. I'm not that sure.
We better start you early when the amounts are small, so it'll
all be set in when the big amounts start to come. Okay?
So 10 cents for charity.
The next 10 cents I call active capital.
Capital meaning, meaning try to make a profit yourself.
We live in a capitalistic society.
Right. Everybody now wants to join capitalism.
That's why the walls are coming down.
Capital belongs in the hands of
the people. That's where the genius is.
So the genius is to try to show a
profit, buy and sell, render service, show a profit.
Now here's what I teach
kids. Profits are better than wages.
Wages are okay, but wages help
you make a lot of money.
Living profits help you make a fortune.
The key is to just understand
philosophically a little simple economic scenario.
And there's all kinds of ways to make a profit.
I'm working on a new book. Here's what it's called.
I think it's going to be
called. Of course, kids should pay taxes.
It's going to be an interesting book.
In California, where I live, kids do pay taxes.
If an eight year old walks into
7-Eleven, buy something that cost a dollar.
The proprietor makes him cough up seven more pennies.
Eight year old says, what's these seven pennies?
Proprietor says that taxes. That's taxes.
Kid says, well, I'm only eight.
Proprietor says, congratulations,
you're my youngest taxpayer.
So in California, kids do pay taxes.
Now, the question is, should they?
Now, the title of my book is.
Of course, kids should pay taxes.
You got it.
Right. The disciple went and caught a fish, found
the miracle coins and paid his taxes and Jesus taxes.
So way back then, Jesus did pay taxes.
Now, the question is, should he?
And the answer, my little book says,
of course, Jesus and kids should pay taxes.
Of course, of course.
If an eight year old wants to ride his bicycle on
the sidewalk instead of in the mud, you have to pay taxes.
Things cost money.
You got to pay taxes.
Aircraft carriers keep tyranny over
there instead of over here.
Aircraft carriers cost money.
It's expensive to run this whole show.
Can't use used missiles.
I mean, you know, it's
expensive to run the whole deal.
Of course, everybody has to pay.
Now, active capital means try
your best to show a profit.
Now, there's many ways to show a profit.
Not just money.
Touch something, leave it better than you found it.
That's a profit.
Some profits are intangible.
Some profits are tangible.
Long before Earth Day, for all sophisticated people, it was very
proper when you left your hotel room to turn out the lights.
All educated people.
Why?
Leave a profit.
It's so easy to flip
the switch and leave a profit.
Some say, well, the hotel gets the profit.
What do you care?
All you need to become is
a person who leaves a profit.
Wow.
I talked to a man who
runs a whole string of apartments.
He said, guess what?
Most people, when they rent an apartment, leave it what?
Trashed worse than they found it.
What kind of a reputation would that be?
Whatever you touch turns to trash.
Whatever you touch gets dirty.
Nothing you touch gets better.
See, that's a poor philosophy.
No wonder it leads to poverty.
Small lives.
As one writer said, living lives of quiet desperation.
This is where it all begins.
Failure to leave a profit when
you can turn out the lights.
Doesn't matter what it is.
Become profit minded.
Profits are better than wages because profit
has the potential to make a fortune.
Wages has the potential to make a living.
So I teach kids take part of your wages.
If you earn the money, take part of it for charity
and part of it to see if you can't make a profit.
And there's all kinds of ways.
My book's going to be full of
all kinds of ways kids can make money.
I teach kids how to have two
bicycles, one to ride and one to rent.
You know, it doesn't take long to get into business.
You don't have to be a genius.
Halfway bright.
You can start showing a profit.
Now, here's the next 10 cents called passive.
Capital.
Meaning let somebody else use the capital.
You provide it.
You're passive.
They're active.
And let them pay you interest.
Profits and interest.
Unique way to make a fortune.
In fact, there's a Bible philosophy.
I teach teenagers this Bible philosophy.
Here's what it teaches.
The borrower is servant to the lender.
Wow.
So where is the power position?
Not a spender.
A lender.
And if I've taught teenagers well, if you ask
them among some of the things you want to be,
you know, when you grow up, you know, as
years pile on, what would you like to be?
I'm telling you among some of the
things that they would like to be.
If they've sat in on my classes or gotten some of my
material, they were say, I want to be one of them lenders.
Powerful position.
Let somebody else use your capital.
Some projects require more capital than any one person has.
So we've got capital pools, whether you
put it in a financial institution or whatever.
Right?
Earn an interest.
Earn a profit.
Right?
Buy a car and sell it
for more than you paid for it.
Why?
Because you leave it better than you found it.
Touch something and leave a profit.
Okay.
It's not just wrapped up in money and economics.
This helps to teach all other scenarios
of life on profit and capital and expenditures.
What to do with your time and what to do with
your life and as well as what to do with your money.
Okay.
Now this little scenario.
I call the ideal.
Now here's what's important to set
up the ideal and work toward it.
Because at first you may not
be able to do these numbers.
Some people are in such desperate situation.
Currently, they got to go.
97, 1, 1 and 1.
I mean, you know, the.
I had to start there.
Start with pennies.
And remember, it's not the amount that counts.
Mr. Schoff gave me the clear.
Situation.
Here it is.
It's not the amount that counts.
It's the plan that counts.
When I met Mr. Schoff, I'm 25 years old.
I said to him, if I had
more money, I'd have a better plan.
He said, no, Mr. Rohn, if you
had a better plan, you'd have more money.
Six years.
In America.
Come on.
It's not the money.
It's not the amount.
It's the plan that counts.
So set up an ideal plan like this.
Now you can rearrange this
and modify it to suit yourself.
But I want you to do this.
You're going to have to do this.
I'm just giving you here as an example.
So set up the ideal and
then start making progress toward it.
Okay, because finally, these numbers are going to change.
If you move on up into the higher area.
Right.
The people I work with around the world couldn't
spend 70 cents out of every dollar would be
obscene.
That'd be too much.
So these numbers are going to change.
It's the money, not the exchange rate.
Right.
these numbers are bound to change. I
don't know what mine are, probably 20% up
here. A lot larger numbers down here.
Okay, so these numbers can change. I'm
just offering you a good
sample philosophy. Remember, philosophy is the
set of the sale. The economy is not the
set of the sale for you. For you, the set
of the sale is your own philosophy,
your own thinking, your own plan, your own
concept. Don't borrow somebody else's
plan. Don't borrow somebody else's
concept. Don't borrow the concept, you
know, spend all you can, cross your
fingers and hope for the best.
Don't borrow that. Develop your own philosophy
and I'm telling you it'll lead you to
unique places. Now, the rest of a lot of
this is on the cassette tapes, but let
me just give you two or three more pieces
of the scenario here. Then I want
to talk about communications and then we're
gonna wrap it up. Okay, here's
two or three more parts to financial
independence. Number one, keep strict
accounts. This is the best
of disciplines, keep strict accounts.
Did you ever hear this expression?
I don't know where it all goes.
Did you ever hear that? I don't know where
it all goes. Oh, we'd love to have you run
our company. You don't know where it all goes. Whoa.
Did you ever hear this? It just gets away from
me. It just seems it just gets away from me.
We'd love to turn the world over you, it
just gets away from you. Come on. You got
to have better disciplines than that. Let that
be the 90%. Let that be the scenario
of the ninety-seven percent, but don't let
it be your scenario. Don't let it
become your philosophy. Keep strict accounts.
Next, a new attitude. I had to
develop a new attitude as well as new concepts. Here's
what I used to say, I hate to pay my taxes.
Shoaff said, well, that's one way to live.
I thought, well, doesn't everybody hate to pay
their taxes? He said, no, no, a few of us
have gotten way past that. He says, once you understand
what taxes are, here's what taxes are in
our governmental system in our society. Taxes is
how you care and feed the goose that
lays the golden eggs. Democracy and liberty and freedom,
free enterprise. Wouldn't you want to feed
the goose that lays the golden eggs?
Somebody says, well, the goose eats too
much. That's probably true. I understand that.
Of course, that's true. But see,
better a fat goose than no goose.
And here's the truth being told.
We all eat too much.
Let not one appetite accuse another.
Of course, the government needs to go
on a diet. So do most of us.
But hey, you still have to care and feed the
goose that lays the golden eggs once you understand that
that's what it's for. See, it is so important,
the right attitude. Here's what I used to say,
I hate to pay my bills. You open
up the mails, nothing but these window envelopes,
bills. I hate to pay my bills. I hate to pay my
bills. I hate to pay my bills. I hate to pay my bills.
Shelf said, well, that's one way to live. I
said, well, doesn't everybody hate to pay their bills?
He said, no, some of us are way beyond that.
I said, is it possible to love
to pay your bills? He said, yes.
Reduce your liabilities, increase your assets.
Wouldn't you love to do that?
So start a whole new attitude here.
Next time you pay $100 on an account,
put a little note in there and say,
with great delight, I send you this $100.
I mean, they don't get many letters like
that. Reduce my liabilities, increase my assets. My
picture's changing. My picture's improving. I love to
pay my bills, keep the money in circulation,
pay my taxes, feed the goose that lays
the golden eggs. It's a matter of attitude.
And here's the last on attitude. Everybody
must pay. Of course, life is called opportunity,
but life is called price.
We all pay. We must all share.
One of the classic stories of
all time from ancient Bible script says,
Jesus one day and his disciples were
standing by the church treasury, synagogue treasury,
watching people as they came by
and put their offering in the treasury.
That wouldn't be a bad idea. Jesus and his
disciples standing by the treasury while everybody walks by.
Jesus said, how are you?
How much was that? How much was that? Interesting.
And the story said, some people
came by, put in big amounts.
Some people came by, put in modest amounts, average amounts.
And the story says, then a little lady comes
by and puts in two pennies in the treasury.
Jesus says to his disciples,
look at that. Look at that.
His disciples said, two pennies,
two pennies. What's two pennies?
Jesus said, no, you don't understand.
She gave more than everybody else.
They said, two pennies is more than everybody else.
He said, yes, because I'm certain that her
two pennies represented most of what she had.
And if you give most of what
you have, then you've given the most.
Wow. What a lesson to learn.
It's not the amount. It's what
it represents of your life that counts.
Now, let me give you the wisdom
of the scenario that did not occur.
And this is the greatest of wisdom.
And in my own particular peculiar brilliance, I have the ability to
record for you what was not recorded in the scenario of the story.
Here's what did not occur, which may teach us one of
the greatest of the wise things that was taught in this scenario.
Here's what did not occur in the scenario.
Jesus did not reach into the treasury and get this
little lady's two pennies and run after her and say,
here, little lady, my disciples and
I have decided that you're so pitiful.
And you're.
So poor that we've decided to
give you back your two pennies.
I'm telling you, that did not occur.
If it would have occurred, she would have been what?
Insulted. She would have rightfully said, I know my two
pennies aren't much, but it represented most of what I had.
And would you insult me by not letting me contribute
what I wanted to contribute, even if it's only two pennies?
I'm telling you, that did not occur.
Here's part of the wisdom of
the story that was not recorded.
Jesus left her pennies in the treasury, meaning
everybody has to pay, even if it's only pennies.
That's the key.
And whether you start with pennies or whether you
start with dollars or whether you start with nothing.
Remember, part of the scenario is to spend.
Of course, part of the scenario is to invest
and part of the scenario is to show a profit.
And part of the scenario is to help take
care of people who can't take care of themselves.
If you'll set up your own philosophy,
I'm not asking you to buy my philosophy.
I'm not asking you to adopt my numbers.
I'm only wanting to provoke you to think for
you to come up with a splendid economic philosophy.
That's got you up early and got you up late.
It's got you thinking and pondering ways to use your resources
and turn it into the dreams you want for the future.
And that's my little story on financial independence.
Okay.
Here's the next to the last subject.
Communication.
How to affect other people with words.
I've got just a little four-point
program here for you to consider.
The whole expanded version now, three days, right?
Three days of all this is
in that package that you're taking home.
So this is called an abbreviated version of
all the rest this one day, video day.
Four steps to good communication.
Here's number one.
First of all, words can work miracles.
That's why communication is so important.
Words can work miracles.
Words are powerful.
Words are almost God-like.
In fact, ancient script says the word was God.
God was the word.
Wow.
Words and God.
I said to my Israeli audience last year,
in the beginning, the story of creation is unique.
It says in the beginning,
Jehovah God spoke and said what?
Got some students here, I'm sure.
In the beginning, Jehovah God spoke and said what?
Let there be light.
And what?
There was light.
Wow.
It looks like words create light.
Is that possible?
I'm telling you it's possible.
Humans can get pretty close.
What if somebody can't?
Possibly see how they could do well, how they could become successful, how they could
transform their lives and their health, their future and their finances spiritually in every other way.
They can't see.
And you come along and share your
story and maybe borrow some other stories.
And by the time you get through with a good
presentation to this person, they say, now I can see.
Before you got here, I was blind.
I was in the dark.
And while you were talking some things.
Dawn dawned on me.
Is it possible to create
light with human intelligence with words?
And the answer is.
Of course.
Here's part of the spectacular opportunity as a human being.
One person talking to another.
It's got so much power, so much potential.
A mother talking to a daughter, a father
talking to a son, salesperson talking to a client.
Nothing more magical and powerful.
awe-inspiring than words have the
ability to dramatically affect people's
lives and futures. So become good
communicator. Let me give you some good
keys to good communication. Here's number
one, have something good to say.
Communication starts with preparation. Getting
ready to speak this year, getting
ready to speak next year. Attend
the classes, read the books, have something
good to say. Here's four good words to
help you to have something good to say.
One is interests, develop a new interest
in people and life, What's going on.
Economics and Politics, Religion,
Social Structure, Possibilities, Opportunities.
Develop a new interest. Here's the
next word, fascination. Goes that step beyond
interest. That's why kids learn so
much that first six years. Fascination. Adults
are walking on ants, kids are
saying don't walk on these ants. I'm
studying these ants. I'm looking at these
ants. Kids are so fascinated. How come an
ant can carry something bigger than he is?
Wow. That's how come they learn so much.
They're fascinated. And here's another
little clue I've learned. Turn
frustration into fascination if you can.
You'll learn more. I've worked on this.
I'm pretty good at it. Out in Los
Angeles I'm on the freeway. My airplane
leaves in 45 minutes. The traffic is
moving not one inch. I
am now fascinated. I'm telling you.
Now it doesn't work every time. That's
true but every time it does work I'm
telling you you'll come away with
more. Learn to be fascinated instead of
frustrated if you possibly can. Turn
that little scenario on for yourself.
Next is sensitivity. You've got to
understand we use the phrase where people
are coming from, where they've been,
what's going on. Sensitivity training is
so important. People not like you,
people that have got challenges and problems
and difficulties. You've got to do your
best to be sensitive to other people,
where they find themselves, the pit they
might be in currently, what's going on. Be
sensitive to that. Here's two of
the greatest things said about Jesus.
One, it said he was touched. He was
touched by where he found some people. He
was touched by the misery he found some
people in. He was touched, he was touched
and here's the other word, he was moved
it said. He was moved, touched and moved.
If you really want to communicate well you
got to be touched and moved. Not just
by your own drama of life but by
the drama you know is going on in other
people's lives. Sensitivity.
How does an adult
forty talk to a child who's twelve? You
got to be sensitive. Not just to your
current situation. One of the best ways
to identify with a child who's twelve
and you're forty is remember when you
were twelve. Go back, go back, remember the
scenario and let it hit you again, let
it touch you again. I don't have any
problems with twelve-year-olds. I remember
almost every day of being twelve.
Twelve is a unique year. One, you're not thirteen.
If I heard it once I heard it a
hundred times. Of course you can't go you're not
a teenager. Wow, I can't wait for
this year to be finished. Remember, that's part
of sensitivity, remember. Apostle. One who
became an apostle, leader of the
Christians was once Saul from Tarsus,
hater and killer of the Christians. After
he was converted and became
a leader became Paul apostle, revered.
Why was he so effective in his language and his
ability to touch people with his words and with his presence?
If you read part of the scenario of his history, he gave an
account of his own life and said, here's why I think I'm so effective.
I remember the pit I came from.
Sure, they call me apostle, but I used
to kill these Christians and I never forget that.
If I want to get in touch with other
people's difficulty, I got to remember my own difficulty.
Let it hurt again.
That's what makes a good performance.
A good actor, a good actress.
The emotion close to the surface
from the remembrance of things past.
And then well-chosen words delivered with emotion.
Powerful.
The last word is knowledge.
You just got to go through exercises like this.
Take the notes, work hard, roll
up your sleeves, go to work.
Gather the knowledge in journals.
Gather the knowledge in notebooks.
Gather the knowledge in a library and
cassettes and videos and every other means.
Gather knowledge.
Don't be lazy in learning.
A major part of communication is preparation.
Now here's the next part of good communication.
Say it well.
One is having something good to say.
Number two is saying it well.
Let me give you a
quick list on saying it well.
Number one, sincerity.
Best place to start.
You want to communicate.
Well, let your sincerity show.
Next is repetition.
The mother of skill.
I've been at this 33 years.
Somebody says, well, you give a pretty good seminar.
I should.
33 years.
Repetition.
Next, brevity.
Sometimes you don't need many
words if you're totally sincere.
I'm telling you.
Jesus presentation.
And gathering up his team called disciples was fairly short.
He just walked around the countryside, took a
look at somebody and said, you follow me.
That's brief.
I mean, you know, that's short.
Now, why could he get by with such few words?
And this takes care of a lot that I've
tried to share with you today called personal development.
Here's why I think Jesus could get by with such few
words for all that he was that he didn't have to say.
Take that scenario home for all that
I am that I don't have to say.
Just a few words could be
dynamic and affecting someone else's life.
A child, a business colleague, a sales client.
Next, vocabulary.
Got to work on your vocabulary.
Some of my friends took a survey
among prisoners working on some rehabilitation program.
They weren't particularly looking for
this, but here's what they found.
There's definitely a relationship.
Between vocabulary and behavior.
And here's what they found out.
The more limited the vocabulary,
the more tendency to poor behavior.
And when you think about it
for a while, it makes sense.
Words are a way of seeing.
And if you don't have a
good vocabulary, you can't see very well.
Can you imagine the mistakes in
judgment when you can't see very well?
Next words are a way of expressing.
What's going on?
What's going on in your head?
What's going on in your heart?
What if you can't see well?
And you can't express well?
You can imagine the tragic scenario of five years of that,
ten years of that, twenty years of that, showing no improvement.
Behavior now becomes a major problem.
And that person's world gets
smaller and smaller and smaller.
Why?
They can't see and they can't express.
And finally, they don't need behavior.
Finally, they don't need much bigger
place than a ten by twelve cell.
Their world is so small
anyway, don't need much bigger place.
I'm asking you to stretch your vocabulary.
I used to put words up
on a three by five card.
I drove a lot back in those days.
But at the end of the
day, I've mastered two or three words.
My oldest daughter, Linda, with my grandkids, starts the
day with what's called the word for the day.
She writes it on a chalkboard.
What's the word for the day?
And the kids memorize that word
and the meaning of the word.
And every once in a while during the
day, she'll say, what's the word for the day?
The last day I was there, the word was superficial.
Natalie's four, Nathaniel's five.
And several times during that day, Linda, my
daughter, would say, what's the word for the day?
Natalie would say superficial.
And she would say, Nathaniel, what does that mean?
On the surface.
Several times during the day.
What's the word for the day?
Superficial.
What does it mean?
On the surface.
If you were to ask my grandkids, the last time
grandpa was here, what was the word for the day?
I'll bet you they'd probably know.
Superficial.
On the surface.
Word for the day.
Why not learn a word a day?
Why not add to your vocabulary so you
can see more, see better, and express better?
Put out in words what's in your heart,
what's in your soul, what's in your mind.
It's important.
So say it well.
Here's number three.
Number one was have something good to say.
Number two, say it well.
Here's number three.
Read your audience.
These are just simple concepts now.
You've got to add some of the details,
but that's what I'm mainly good for is concepts.
Read your audience.
If you're talking to a child, you've
got to study the face of the child.
You've got to study a little body language.
You've got to study what's going on so you'll
know whether to shift gears, come on a little
stronger, ease off a little, might be
too strong, search for another illustration, soft,
strong.
A lot of that is dictated by reading your audience.
When I first started lecturing, I had some challenges here.
I was so absorbed in my notes lecturing like this.
I'm telling you, in those early days, the
audience could have left and I'd have kept
right on going.
I didn't know what was going on down here.
I didn't know what was going on over here.
I didn't have any idea what was happening
over here, whether I should come on a little
stronger, ease back.
I didn't know.
I couldn't read my audience.
So, read your audience.
A prospect, read.
Now let me give you some ways to read.
Number one, by what you see.
Body language tells us some things.
How to shift gears, whether
to go on, whether to stop.
If you're talking to somebody and they're
leaning toward the door, that means you gotta
hurry, right?
They're not gonna be here long.
Body language.
Guy's got his arms folded, chin tucked down.
You got your work cut out for you.
You're gonna have to reach deep in your bag.
Find some extraordinary stories.
This one's not gonna be easy.
What tells you that?
Reading what you see.
Here's the next one.
Read what you hear.
You got to read a child's impatience.
Kids don't mind telling you
whether they're bored or impatient.
Kids' attention span is short.
It doesn't last long.
You gotta get it said.
You start talking to a child, 30 seconds
they say, how long is this gonna take?
Whoa.
Read.
Listen.
Listen to what they're saying.
Listen for the response.
Now you'll know whether to shift gears,
change your language, find a new illustration, soften,
stronger.
Read your audience.
Read what you see.
Read what you hear.
And here's one of the most important.
Read what you feel.
Now women are probably better at this than
men when it comes to picking up emotional
signals.
Men, they can see and men, they can hear.
But it takes a little training for a
man to pick up those emotional signals that are
so important so you don't say the wrong stuff.
Because it's so easy to make a mistake in language.
What if you meant to say to someone you
care about, what if you meant to say, what's troubling
you?
And instead you said, what's wrong with you?
What's wrong with you?
Communication.
So read the emotional signals.
If we could learn from the women on
this, the most women have this uncanny antenna picking
up this stuff.
Stop.
Woman says it doesn't feel right.
I mean, what does that mean?
It doesn't feel right.
Well, when women have got the women have
got it, though, seems to be built in, especially
danger.
Women pick it up quicker than men.
It's built in, I think.
Way back, right?
Man was the provider.
Mama was the protector at home.
So she picked up this scenario
of danger, I think, these signals.
But they are good.
In the middle of the night, mama wakes up.
The baby cries.
Mama wakes up.
Papa sleeps.
The faintest cry.
Mama's awake.
Or she nudges her husband and says,
go look, go look, something isn't right.
He says, what do you mean it isn't right?
She says, no, go look.
He said, hey, everything's okay.
She says, go look.
He says, okay.
And he gets out of bed, goes downstairs.
The front door is open.
How did she know that?
We don't know.
I mean, she just knows.
She just knows.
But I'm telling you, it's so valuable in communication
to be able to pick up the emotional signals
as well.
It's what you see and
as well as what you hear.
It's so important.
But women are good.
Ancient scenario says this.
There are shepherds and there
are sheep and there are wolves.
What a good life scenario.
But it doesn't stop there.
This ancient scenario says also some wolves are so clever.
They've learned to dress up like sheep.
Sheep.
Now you've got to have a woman.
Got to have a woman.
Man says, looks like a sheep.
Talks like a sheep.
Woman says, ain't no sheep.
Take my word for it.
They know.
Read.
Pick up the signals.
Don't ignore the signals.
Develop this.
This is a personal development scenario.
Communication, financial independence and all the rest.
Now here's the last part.
Intensity.
Words mixed with emotion.
Words mixed with hate.
Words mixed with love.
Words mixed with faith.
Words mixed with courage.
That's what's powerful.
Words have a certain effect, but words
loaded with emotion have an incredible effect.
If I had a little straight pen.
Right?
This guy buys a shirt.
It's got all these little pins in it.
I take out all these pins.
If I took one of those little
straight pins and I threw it at you.
And let's say it reached you and hit you
in the face or hit you in the hand.
You'd feel it.
This little straight pin.
That means I got to you with my words.
But what if I took that little straight pin
and wired it to the end of an iron bar?
About that long.
See, I could drive that pin through your heart.
The pin is the words.
The iron bar is the emotions.
The emotions.
Here's the best I could share with you.
Put more of you into what you say.
Don't be casual in language.
Don't be casual in words.
Casualness leads to casualties on
the freeway and in communication.
Don't be lazy in learning good
communication and put more of you.
Now, here's the last thought.
The emotions must be measured.
It can't be too much for
the occasion if it's not called for.
In leadership, we teach don't
shoot a cannon at a rabbit.
It's effective, but you've gotten a more rabbit.
So here's some of the
most powerful scenario in communication.
Here it is.
Well-chosen words mixed with measured emotion.
The basis of affecting people with good communication.
And one last point on communication.
The more you care, the stronger you can be.
The more you care as a mother,
the stronger you can be with your children.
The more you care as a
father, the stronger you can be.
leader, the stronger you can be.
In helping to solve problems, getting
on somebody's case, the more you care.
But you gotta care.
I don't mind a minister consigning my
soul to hellfire for my sinful ways.
I don't mind that.
If he believes it, I don't mind him
consigning my soul to hellfire for my sinful ways.
As long as he does it
with tears and not with joy.